<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The books opened Being several discourses on Rev. 20. 14. By Henry Pendlebury, A.M. late minister of the Gospel at Rochdale in Lancashire; author of the Plain representation of transubstantiation.</title>
            <author>Pendlebury, Henry, 1626-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829163</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;  1974:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The books opened Being several discourses on Rev. 20. 14. By Henry Pendlebury, A.M. late minister of the Gospel at Rochdale in Lancashire; author of the Plain representation of transubstantiation.</title>
                  <author>Pendlebury, Henry, 1626-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi, 7-116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.D. for Ann Unsworth of Manchester; and sold by Jonathan Robinson at the Golden Lion in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XX, 14 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BOOKS OPENED.</p>
            <p>Being ſeveral DISCOURSES on REV. 20.14.</p>
            <p>By HENRY PENDLEBURY, A. M. late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire;</hi> Author of the <hi>Plain Repreſentation of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Ann <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſworth</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter;</hi> and ſold by <hi>Jonathan Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33599:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33599:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33599:3"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:33599:3"/>
            <head>The EPISTLE to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are two things which if firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed and duly conſidered, would have a great Influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Men and Womens Lives, <hi>viz. Firſt,</hi> That they are mortal. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Creatures. It is the indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Statute-Law of Heaven that never will be repealed or diſpenſed withal, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. Death is a Debt which all Men owe, and how ſoon the great Creditor may exact it, none can tell: We are all here as Tenants at Will in Cottages of Clay, whoſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is in the Duſt. Theſe earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles are continually mouldring down about our Ears, do what we can by Food and Phyſick to patch them up for a little while. There is no Man liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death. And Death hath always Judgment attending at the very Heels of it. And <hi>as the Tree falls, ſo it lies: As Death leaves us, Judgment will find us.</hi> And as it is with us when we go out of this World, ſo it will fare with us for ever.
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:33599:4"/>
This ſhort uncertain Life we have here is the only time of Preparation we have for another World. Death ſets Men on the other ſide the Water, there will be no work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, no praying nor repenting, and believing, and ſeeking to get our Sins par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and an Intereſt in Chriſt, and a Right to Heaven: if this Work be to be done then, we ſhall be undone to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. If we once die in a Chriſtleſs and graceleſs Condition, we ſhall periſh for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo to all Eternity. There will be no Time then to correct former Miſtakes. At Death we muſt all appear before an impartial Judg, to receive our final conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive determining Sentence to a fixed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal unchangeable State of Miſery or Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in another World. And things will then appear quite otherwiſe than they were ſtated, and did appear here. Then all Vizards and Masks will be pluck'd off, and naked Breaſts will be in faſhion: What hath been here concealed, will then be made manifeſt: what hath been ſpoken in ſecret, will then be told on the Houſe-top: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hid but ſhall then be made manifeſt. At this opening Day there will be a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the Sons of God: then all
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:33599:4"/>
the Sincerity and ſecret Graces and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Believers will be openly declared, and all thoſe Marks and Evidences of the Truth of Grace, (which here are often clouded and obſcured) will evidently appear: And all the ſecret Wickedneſs and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, and Falſe-heartedneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, will then be diſcovered and laid open. And the Apoſtle lets us know what an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence (the Belief and Conſideration of) this had upon himſelf, and other Miniſters of the Goſpel, to quicken them to Diligence and Faithfulneſs in their Miniſterial Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>2 Cor. 5.9, 10.</hi> We muſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; <hi>1ſt.</hi> [All], without Exception, High and Low, Rich and Poor, Young and Old, Miniſters and People; there will be no declining or eſcaping of it. <hi>2dly.</hi> [All], in our own Perſons, without a Proxy; there will be no hiring of another to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for us, every one of us muſt give an Account of himſelf to God, <hi>Rom. 14.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the great Deſign of the worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author in theſe enſuing Sermons, is to quicken and direct Perſons to prepare and make ready for this opening Day. And herein he ſhews himſelf a skilful Workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, dividing
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:33599:5"/>
the Word of Truth aright, and giving to every one their Portion. He doth not put the two-edged Sword of the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſilken Scabbard, and flouriſh it in the Air; but dexterouſly weilds it that it might reach the Conſciences of Men: he ſpeaks plainly but pertinently and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially; his Words are not only intelligible, but alſo penetrating. And tho theſe plain Diſcourſes are poſthumous, (and want the poliſhing that he was able to have given them, had he deſigned them for the Preſs) yet they are genuine, copied from his own Notes: and you have the trueſt Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of him in the conſtant Courſe of his Preaching amongst his People. Some ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtians that were affected with them themſelves, have deſired to have them printed, that others might ſhare in the like Benefit with them. And that thy Heart may be warmed (as others have been upon the reading of them) and thou be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and helped in this Preparation for the great opening Day, as it was the Deſign of the Author in preaching of them, ſo it is of others in the publiſhing them, and of none more than of one of the meaneſt and unworthieſt of Chriſt's Miniſters,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33599:5"/>
            <head>THE BOOKS Opened.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REV. xx. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God; and the Books were opened: and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life: and the Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Works.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that <hi>we muſt all appear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. Of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, and which we muſt all come unto, we have a Deſcription in this part of Sacred Writ, as it was ſhewed unto <hi>John</hi> in a Viſion; where are ſet forth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon of the Judg, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. who is deſcribed,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33599:6"/>(1.) By his Poſture, <hi>Sitting;</hi> the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Poſture of Judges in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice and Judgment, and a Token of Dominion and Authority.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) By the Place where he ſat, <hi>a great white Throne:</hi> Not in a Manger, as at his firſt Coming; not on the Ground, as when in Fleſh he dwelt amongſt us; nor on a Croſs, as at his leaving the World, but on a great white Throne.</p>
            <p>He that lay in a Manger, that ſtood at Man's Bar falſly accuſed, and wickedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; he that hung upon the Tree, ſhall ſit ſupreme Judg; <hi>Sedebit Judex qui ſtetit ſub Judice.</hi> What this Throne is, or of what it ſhall be made, (tho ſome ſay the Angels, others a glorious Rainbow, others a bright Cloud) Scripture being ſilent, you muſt not know of me.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) By his Power and Glory. <hi>From whoſe Face the Earth and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no Place for them.</hi> At his firſt Appearance <hi>Herod</hi> ſeeking his Life, he is forced to fly, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.14. At his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and glorious Coming, Heaven and Earth ſhall flee away, not being able to abide his Majeſty and Power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſons to be judged; <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>And I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God:</hi> the Dead of all ſorts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. We muſt here include thoſe that ſhall be found alive at this day, who ſhall paſs through a Change that ſhall be to them inſtead of Death.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33599:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. The Form of this Judgment; the manner how the Judg ſhall proceed, <hi>viz.</hi> by Books that ſhall be opened.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sentence is paſſed on the Parties brought to Judgment according to what is found written in the Books when thus open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>And the Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books according to their Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Execution of this Sentence; <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>And Death and Hell were caſt into the Lake of Fire: This is the ſecond Death. And whoſoever was not found written in the Book of Life, was caſt into the Lake of Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words which are the Subject of the enſuing Diſcourſe, contain in them the third Particular in this Deſcription, <hi>ſc.</hi> the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Proceſs in this great Work, <hi>the Books ſhall be opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>Book</hi> is in Scripture uſed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Properly, for a Volume wherein ſomething is written, or for the things writ in that Volume; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Improperly and metaphorically, for the certain Knowledg and Remembrance that one hath of a Perſon or Matter, and all the Circumſtances thereto belonging; Mal. 3.16. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another; and the Lord heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and heard it, and a Book of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was written before him.</hi> According to this twofold Acceptation of the Word,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33599:7"/>
God is ſaid to have a double Book.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Materialis, i. e.</hi> the Bible, which is called <hi>the Book of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 34.16. Luke 4.17. the Book containing the Mind, and Will, and Ways of God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Metaphoricus,</hi> which is aſcrib'd to him after the manner of Men, who uſe to note thoſe things in Books that they would preſerve the Knowledg of. Thus there is a threefold Book figuratively aſcribed to him, <hi>viz.</hi> 1ſt. The Book of Providence, which is the certain Knowledg he hath of all Perſons, Actions, and Things, with all their Circumſtances, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8. &amp; 139.16. 2dly. The Book of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. This is the certain Knowledg he hath of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and Reprobate. 3dly. The Book of Univerſal Judgment, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. We are not to underſtand this Phraſe literally, as if there ſhould be ſome material Books pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and opened at this day. No, the Lord hath neither Need nor Uſe for them. But it muſt be interpreted metaphorically, as a Form uſed for the Help of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſpoken,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Alluſion to Courts of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Judicature, into which are brought, and wherein are produced Charges, Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, Proofs, Depoſitions of Witneſſes, Confeſſions of Parties, and all other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that contain Matter of Fact relating to ſuch Cauſes as are to be try'd.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33599:7"/>2. To ſhow that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be as accurate and particular in the Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Trial,<note place="margin">Durham, <hi>p.</hi> 743.</note> and as juſt in the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as if all had been recorded. Nothing ſhall be omitted, nor the leaſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance miſtaken, but things ſhall be ſo equal in themſelves, and ſo manifeſted to others, as if an exact Regiſter had been kept and then publiſhed.</p>
            <p>From the Words obſerve;
<q>
                  <hi>That in the great Day of Judgment the Books ſhall be opened:</hi> or, <hi>There is a Day a coming when the Books ſhall be opened.</hi> The Judgment was ſet, and the Books were opened, <bibl>
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That this Truth may be prepared for Application, it muſt be enquired,
<list>
                  <item>I. What Books they are that ſhall be opened?</item>
                  <item>II. What the opening of theſe Books implies?</item>
                  <item>III. Who they are theſe Books are to be opened about?</item>
                  <item>IV. About what are theſe Books to be opened?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. What Books are they that ſhall be opened? They are of three ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33599:8"/>Thoſe wherein,
<list>
                  <item>1. All things have been recorded.</item>
                  <item>2. All things ſhall be diſcovered.</item>
                  <item>3. All things ſhall be judged.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Thoſe wherein all things have been recorded, and they are;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Book of Divine Omniſcience. Here all things ſtand on Record, and will hence be as certainly known as had they been writ in a Book: for there is not <hi>any Creature that is not manifeſt in his Sight; but all things are naked and open to the Eyes of him with whom we have to do,</hi> Heb. 4.13. <hi>His Eyes are upon the Ways of Man, and he ſeeth all his Goings: There's no Darkneſs nor Shadow of Death where the Workers of Iniquity may hide themſelves,</hi> Job. 34.21, 22. <hi>He knows our Works,</hi> Rev. 2.13. <hi>There is not a Word in our Tongue, but lo he knows it,</hi> Pſal. 139.4. Here are our Thoughts writ: <hi>Thou underſtandeſt my Thoughts afar off,</hi> v. 2. <hi>No Thought can be with-holden from thee,</hi> Job 42.2. Here are the Hearts deſcribed: 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>The Lord ſearcheth all Hearts, and underſtandeth all the Imaginations of the Thoughts.</hi> The Lord knows, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers all the Actions, Thoughts and Words of all Men, and ſhall make it appear at this day, that he doth ſo as fully and plainly as if he had kept a Diary from the Beginning of the World to the end thereof, and therein writ in order every particular Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every individual Man and Woman.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33599:8"/>
O remember this, God ſees thee round about always, can tell all that thou doſt; and this Book wherein all is written ſhall one day be opened!</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Book of Conſcience, this carries all our Actions in it; <hi>Volumen grande quo omnia conſcribuntur;</hi> 
               <q>It is a great Volume in which all we do is writ.</q> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> takes that other Book mentioned in the Text to be the Book of Conſcience, which is the Book of each Man's Life, wherein all the Paſſages thereof are recorded. Tho this Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation agree not with this Place, yet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ſuch a Book as he here deſcribes: <hi>Quocunque vadis, ubicunque es, ſemper Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia tua tecum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Whitherſoever thou go, where-ever thou art, thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is always with thee, carrying in it whatever thou put'ſt therein, whether good or bad.</q> Conſcience is not always ſpeaking nor always chiding, (many have ſilenced it) but it is always writing; when we are at our Tables, when on our Beds, when we are alone or in Company it keeps an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Account: and this Book alſo ſhall be opened.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Books ſhall then be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereby all things ſhall be clearly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and atteſted. Theſe are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Book of Divine Omniſcience. As all things are incloſed herein, ſo this ſhall then be opened; and all the things contained in it thereby diſcloſed. He will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33599:9"/>
by the opening of this make manifeſt to all, that which is now hid from Men and Angels, and only known to himſelf. God knows all things, and will make all Men know that he doth ſo, by ſetting in order before their Eyes all things at this day; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Book of Conſcience. Herein all things are writ; and by the opening hereof ſhall appear: <hi>Quod in cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia occultum fuit, id omnibus manifeſtum fiet.</hi> In this day Conſcience ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned and awakened, Memories ſhall be rouz'd and ſtrengthned, all paſt things ſhall appear new, and come in freſh upon the Sons of Men. Then every Thought of thy Heart, every Word of thy Mouth, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Action of thy Life with the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof; then every Day of Grace, and how thou haſt ſpent it, every Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of doing and getting Good, and how thou haſt improv'd it, ſhall come in as new as that which thou didſt the laſt Day or Hour. Yea, the things that are now gone from thee, (as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Dream from him) and that thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten what they were at ſuch a time, in ſuch a Place, among ſuch Company, forty or fifty Years ago, theſe ſhall come in and be as livelily preſented to thy view, as when newly acted. O think on this! It is a common Saying, that Conſcience is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Witneſſes: You carry this Witneſs in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33599:9"/>
your own Boſoms; <hi>Nocte diéque ſuum geſtant in pectore teſtem;</hi> which when the opening Day comes, will proclaim all as on the Houſe-top.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Book of Satan's Accuſation: He is called <hi>the Accuſer,</hi> Rev. 12.10. This is one Part of his Buſineſs now, but he will eſpecially appear to be ſo when he at the Great Day ſhall come with his Regiſter wherein he now inſerts our Actions.</p>
            <p>There is a Relation of a Demon that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at <hi>Maſcon</hi> in <hi>France</hi> in the Houſe of a godly Miniſter, who there ſpoke and acted many things, among which there are theſe two remarkable Stories.</p>
            <p>One time the Demon ſpeaking profanely, a grave Divine then preſent religiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked him; to whom he anſwer'd, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, you are very holy and ſerious in this Company, you were not ſo when ſinging ſuch a baudy Song in ſuch a Tavern, which the Demon rehears'd before the Company. This the Divine confeſs'd he did in his Youth; yet when he had forgot it, and perhaps that ever he ſung it, the Devil readily remembers it as if but done that Day. The other is of a Lawyer who came out of Curioſity, and would urge ſeveral Queſtions, which when the Demon had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, he further adds, Now Sir I have told you what you demanded, I muſt next tell you what you demand not, and then diſcovered many of his unequal Dealings,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33599:10"/>
which made him appear to be a diſhoneſt Man. The Devil is a buſy Body, preſent at our Tables, at our Recreations, with us in the Shop, in the Market, and Field, with us in ſolemn Aſſemblies, with us when engaged in private and ſecret Duties, ever ſpying and liſtning to ſee and hear what we do or ſay: no Place is ſo ſecret, we cannot act ſo privately but his piercing Eye will find us out, and he hath a ſure Memory which will not permit any thing we do to paſs in Oblivion; he will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly when this opening Day comes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch a Catalogue of the Sinners Works as they little think of; he will bring his Bill of their Ways, as the Patriarchs brought <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Coat to <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſaying, Is not this the Coat of thy Son? ſo is not this, Sinners, the Coat of your Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which you have here ſpotted with Oaths, there with Drunkenneſs, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place with Uncleanneſs, and all over with variety of Tranſgreſſions?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Book of Human Teſtification, or Sinners mutual Accuſations. Now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Husbands and Wives, Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Maſters and Servants, are leading one another into Temptations: Then they ſhall accuſe and witneſs againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as our Saviour ſays in another Caſe, Luke 12.52, 53. <hi>The Father ſhall be divided againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Mother againſt the Daughter, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33599:10"/>
the Daughter againſt the Mother.</hi> So at this great Day, <hi>A Man's Foes ſhall be thoſe of his own Houſhold,</hi> Matth. 10.36. Parents ſhall riſe againſt their own Children, Children ſhall riſe againſt their Parents; then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall witneſs againſt their Servants, and Servants againſt their Maſters. O the Cries, the Complaints that will be of Husbands, Wives, Children, Servants of the ſame Houſe againſt each other! A young Man going to execution, deſired to ſpeak with his Mother in the Ear, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of whiſpering bit off her Ear, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of her as the promoter of his Death, becauſe ſhe did not in his Youth chaſtiſe him for his Faults, but by her fond Indulgence imboldened him in his Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. Thus at the opening Day Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will appear againſt their Parents; Lord, theſe Parents were inſtrumental to bring me into the World, but they were alſo my Souls Murderers, training me up in Ignorance, teaching me by their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to lie, ſwear, and ſteal, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering me to be vile and profane. Parents will at the great Aſſizes appear againſt Children; Lord, this Child was Stubborn, Rebellious, Untractable. Servants ſhall give Teſtimony againſt Maſters, Lord, we were ſo long in ſuch a Family, but never ſaw any thing of Religion in it; we ſate down and roſe up from our Tables like Brutes, we never knew what it was to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33599:11"/>
have the Doors ſhut in the Evening, nor opened in the Morning with the Key of Prayer, and reading of the Scriptures. <hi>Sic, ſic in Domo propria habeo Accuſatores, Teſtes, Judices, &amp; Tortores.</hi> Bern. "Thus, thus, ſays one, <q>I have in my own Houſe, Accuſers, Witneſſes, Judges, and Tormentors!</q> When you are tempted to ſin by Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Neighbours, ſay as the Man to <hi>Joab,</hi> when reproved for not killing <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> 2 Sam. 18.11, 12, 13. <hi>There is no Matter hid from the King, and thou thy ſelf wouldſt have ſet thy ſelf againſt me.</hi> So the King, even the King of Kings, hath commanded that we abſtain from Sin and from the appearance of Evil; and if I ſhould break his Command, it cannot be hid from his omniſcient Eye; nay, you who now tempt, will in the great Day accuſe me.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Book of the Creature. It's ſaid of the wicked Man; Job 20.27. <hi>That the Heavens ſhall reveal his Iniquity, and the Earth ſhall riſe up againſt him.</hi> All the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhall by their common Teſtimony diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe his Wickedneſs: Ver. 28. <hi>The increaſe of his Houſe ſhall depart.</hi> The Vulgar ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, <hi>Apertum erit germen Domus ipſius,</hi> the Branch of his Houſe ſhall be opened. Upon which <hi>Sanctius</hi> making theſe words explicatory of the foregoing Verſe, thus gloſſes, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>The Heaven and the Earth ſhall reveal his Iniquities, by diſcovering
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33599:11"/>
whence, how, and by what means his Branch hath grown, his Increaſe hath come; by what Frauds, Oaths, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion the Furniture of his Houſe was compaſſed, that this came by Lies, and that by wronging others.</q> Thus tho he miſtakes the Text, he gives us a Gloſs which is in it ſelf ſolid. The Prophet tells us, Hab. 2.11. <hi>That the Stone ſhall cry out of the Wall, and the Beam out of the Timber ſhall anſwer it.</hi> The very Materials of thoſe ſtately Palaces, or whatever Houſes are built by Cheating, or poſſeſſed by Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, as they call to Heaven for Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, being procured by Injuſtice; ſo they ſhall unitedly witneſs againſt their Erectors or Owners; the Stones of ſuch Walls will cry, Lord, we were laid here by Violence; the Beams ſhall anſwer, We were laid here by Fraud. They are not a few who now live in curious Houſes, that will be dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſſes againſt them at this opening Day. Says the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 5.3. <hi>Your Gold and Silver is cankered, and the Ruſt thereof ſhall be a Witneſs againſt you, and ſhall eat your Fleſh as it were Fire.</hi> This will be brought as an Evidence of your Covetouſneſs, and will beget in you ſuch ſtinging Reflections as ſhall gnaw upon you with Anguiſh and Torment. Ver. 4. <hi>And behold the Hire of your Labourers which have reaped down your Fields, which is of you kept back by Fraud, crieth, and the Cries of them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33599:12"/>
which have reaped, are entred into the Ears of the Lord of Sabaoth.</hi> One obſerves that the ſame word in the Hebrew, ſignifies both a Wedg of Gold, and a Tongue; and ſome ſay that <hi>Achan</hi>'s Wedg had the ſhape of a Tongue: Surely Gold, Wealth, Eſtates ill got, will have many Tongues, and cry aloud at the great Day of opening the Books. Then the corrupt Judg will hear of his Bribes and perverting Juſtice; then the unjuſt Lawyers Eſtate will cry againſt him; then the Poſſeſſions of Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Landlords will declare that they were got by wracking poor Tenants; then 'twill be the Language of the full Bags of idle Miniſters, that they were fill'd by ſtarving immortal Souls; then the Treaſures of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Mammoniſts will acknowledg them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the Products of Uſury, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Book of the Talents wherewith Men are intruſted, ſhall be opened at this opening Day, and theſe when opened will bring to light all the Days, Means, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and Opportunities of Grace that Men have had; all the Truths, and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that have been preached to, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on them, what Pains have been taken, and how much done that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. One obſerves that God is very curious in Scripture to record the Time how long his faithful Servants lived on Earth; and ſays he, among other Reaſons this is not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33599:12"/>
the leaſt, <hi>ſc.</hi> to convince us that he intends to reckon with thoſe who lived with them, for every Year, yea, Day and Hour they had them amongſt 'em; they ſhall know they had a Prophet, a Husband, a Parent, a Maſter that was Godly, and that they had them ſo long, and God will know of them what Uſe they made of them. [<hi>Gurn. Chriſt. Arm.</hi> Part 2. Pag. 262.] Another obſerves, that the Year and Month, and Day, when the Word of the Lord came to the Prophets, ſtands upon record in Sacred Writ, (as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.1, 2.) to teach us that all our Betruſtments with all their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are now recorded, and will at this Day be made manifeſt. Then will be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Year, the Month, the Day, when ſuch a Sermon was preached, ſuch a Truth urged, when ſuch a Miniſter was ſent with the Lord's Meſſage among you. In this opening Day, Miniſters will open their Mouths, We preached ſo long to you; Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths and Sermons will ſpeak, We were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo long to you; Prayers will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that they were put up for you ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Throne of Grace; Truths, now impriſoned, ſhall then ſpeak; yea, the Duſt ſhaken off from the Feet of thoſe Miniſters you deſpiſe and will not hear, ſhall ſpeak againſt you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Books ſhall then be opened, whereby all things ſhall be examined, try'd, and judged. As in earthly Courts,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33599:13"/>
when Matters of Fact are opened and proved, then the Statutes are alſo produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and Sentence is paſt on ſuch Matters according to the determination of the Law: So at the great Tribunal when the Books of Record, the Books of Evidence and Proof are opened, then ſhall alſo be opened the Law whereby Matters ſhall be finally adjudicated, and this is the Holy Scripture: The Holy Bible being the Law-Book of the great King, is now the Rule of our Lives, and ſhall be the Rule of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the opening Day. Chriſt himſelf, who is the Judg, tells us, John 12.48. <hi>The Word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judg him at the laſt Day.</hi> This the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſes, Rom. 2.16. <hi>In the Day when God ſhall judg the Secrets of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel.</hi> Who ſhall judg? <hi>God:</hi> What ſhall he judg? <hi>The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Men;</hi> not only their outward Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are manifeſt to all, but their moſt hidden Sins, and ſecret Duties, their inward Purpoſes, Deſigns, and Aims: By whom? <hi>By Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> By what Rule? <hi>According to my Goſpel;</hi> the Goſpel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, and preached by me; Men ſhall be judged according to their Works, their Works by this Word: The final Sentence paſſed at this Day, ſhall, be but a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and manifeſt Declaration of that Judgment which the Lord hath in his Written Law already paſſed upon Men;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33599:13"/>
that which is now ſaid ſhall then be done. Now the word ſays, He that <hi>believeth on him, ſhall have everlaſting Life,</hi> John 3.16. Then Believers ſhall be crown'd with a Crown of Life. Now the word ſays, That <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9. That the Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell. Look what Sentence this Law now paſſes on thee, the ſame will Chriſt pronounce in this Day; for this is the Book that muſt be opened, and which he will proceed by in giving Judgment. Thus you ſee what Books are to be opened.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The next thing to be conſidered is, what the opening of the Books implies. and it doth denote,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A manifeſtation of Mens Works, that they ſhall come to Light. While a Book is ſhut we are ignorant what is in it, but when it's open every one may ſee and know what's therein writ: So many of Mens Works, both Good and Bad, are like a claſped or ſealed Book, ſecret and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; but in this Day they ſhall be like a Book open, legible to every one. 1 Cor. 4.5. <hi>Therefore judg nothing before the Time come, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of Darkneſs, and will manifeſt the Counſels of the Heart.</hi> When the Lord comes, he will make great Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, and bring to light things that are now Secret. <hi>Some Mens Sins</hi> (ſays the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33599:14"/>
Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24, 25.) <hi>are open before hand, going before to Judgment; and ſome Men they follow after. Likewiſe alſo the good Works of ſome are manifeſt before hand, and they that are otherwiſe cannot be hid.</hi> Tho theſe Verſes are taken to have another meaning, yet I may as ſome, make this Gloſs on them, <hi>i. e.</hi> Some Mens Sins are open, notorious, appear to all now in this Life, they ſhew their Sin as <hi>Sodom;</hi> and ſome Mens Sins they are kept ſecret to the Day of Judgment, there's no noiſe heard, no notice taken of them in the World, but theſe follow after, to be opened at this Day. Likewiſe the good Works of ſome are evident, cannot be denied; and they that are otherwiſe cannot be hid, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe good things in the Saints that are not manifeſt, but are either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed by themſelves, or miſtaken and miſrepreſented by, others, ſhall come to light; ſecret Duties ſhall come abroad, wronged Innocence and Integrity ſhall be cleared. This is the firſt thing this open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imports, <hi>ſc.</hi> a diſcovery of Mens Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, a manifeſtation of their Works; this ſhall be done by the opening of the Books of Record.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Teſtification of the Works mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, that they ſhall not only come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but alſo be ſo fully evidenced, and clearly prov'd, that no Man ſhall be able to deny any part thereof. Sometimes in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33599:14"/>
Mens Courts, the Priſoner at the Bar de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the Matter of Fact that he is charged with, pleads not Guilty, and ſtands upon his own Juſtification; but when Witneſſes come in one after another, and depoſe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, poſitively, punctually, and directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, bringing undeniable Evidence, then he is forced to confeſs. Thus now many are ready to deny their Deeds of Darkneſs; ay, but ſo many Witneſſes ſhall come in at this Day, and with ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as will force Confeſſions. O Sirs! the Secrets of Sinners ſhall be ſo fully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, atteſted, and proved, that they ſhall confeſs: and the Saints that have been ſlandered, aſpers'd, defam'd, and wronged, ſhall have their Innocence ſo fully evidenced that the World ſhall ſee it and be ſatisfied. This is a ſecond thing this opening implies, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Matters ſhall be found, and fully made out as they are in themſelves, with their ſeveral Circumſtances, which will be done by the opening of the Books whereby all things ſhall be diſcovered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Determination or Judgment to be paſſed on the Works of Men thus manifeſted and made out, that there ſhall be a final determining, and definitive Sentence paſſed on them. This is another thing; this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening is an opening to paſs Sentence, as Judges after full Trial open and read the Sentence out of a Book; an opening to abſolve or condemn, therefore it follows
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33599:15"/>
immediately in the Words, <hi>the Dead were judged,</hi> that is, Sentence was paſſed on them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. You have ſeen what Books ſhall be opened, and what the opening of them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; the next Inquiry may be this, About whom muſt they be opened? To this, I ſay, they ſhall be opened about all Men Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, the whole Off-ſpring deſcending from <hi>Adam by ordinary Generation,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception. This will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Univerſality of Scripture-Aſſertions in this preſent Caſe. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaking of this, brings in, (1.) All Men. Rom. 14.10. <hi>We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</hi> Ver. 11. <hi>For it is written, As I live, ſaith the Lord, every Knee ſhall bow to me, and every Tongue ſhall confeſs to God.</hi> What doth the Apoſtle hence infer? Ver. 12. <hi>So then every one of us ſhall give account of himſelf to God.</hi> 2 Cor 5.10. (2.) All Nations. Mat. 25.32. <hi>Before him ſhall be gathered all Nations:</hi> not a few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but whole Nations; not a few Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but all Nations. (3.) All the World <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a Day at which he will judg the World in Righteouſneſs, by the Man whom he hath ordained.</hi> Obſerve, here is a Day appointed, the End for which it was appointed, <hi>ſc.</hi> to judg; the Object of this Judgment, the World, the whole World; whoſoever is of the World ſhall come to this opening Day.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33599:15"/>2. From the ſpecial Diſtribution the Scriptures make in this Caſe, diſtributing the Parties that are to come to this open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; (1.) Into Quick and Dead; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt is ſtiled <hi>Judg of Quick and Dead,</hi> Acts 10.42. 2 Tim. 4.1. (2.) Into great and ſmall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. the King and the Beggar, the Rich and the Poor, the Old and the Young; they that have been ſo high that they have judged others, and they that have been ſo low that their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been taken away. (3.) Into Good and Bad, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Solomon</hi> there reports what he ſaw practiſed in the Place of Juſtice and Judgment, <hi>ſc.</hi> he ſaw their publick Injuſtice, the Good oppreſſed, the Bad exalted: Upon which he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates his Thoughts, or that which was his Comfort againſt theſe unjuſt, unequal dealings of Men; and it was this, that God would have a Day of judging all Men, and all things over again. <hi>I ſaid in my Heart,</hi> (I comforted my ſelf in this) <hi>God ſhall judg the Righteous and the Wicked: for there is a Time there,</hi> (where, why, with God before his Tribunal) <hi>for every Purpoſe, and for every Work,</hi> Ver. 17. Thus God ſhall judg the Righteous with a Judgment of Diſcuſſion and Approbation; the Wicked with a Judgment of Diſcuſſion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; the Perſons that muſt come to this opening are thus diſtinguiſhed: Now all Men come under one of theſe Ranks,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33599:16"/>
either they are Great or Small, Good or Bad, therefore all ſhall be judged.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Now you have ſeen about whom; the next thing to be conſidered is, about what they are to be opened; what things they are that the Books ſhall diſcover, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and determine when opened? Theſe are the Actions of Men, the Works, Words, and Thoughts of Men. Take for this but theſe two Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The one is <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. where the things to be brought to Judgment are deſcribed, (1.) Generally, <hi>every Work;</hi> none ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, be pretermitted, or paſſed by, each one ſhall come in its Place; for there is a Time for every Work. (2.) Particularly, in regard, (1.) Of their manner, every open Work ſhall come in, none of theſe ſhall eſcape, no, not <hi>an idle Word,</hi> Mat. 12.36. Every ſecret Work; the <hi>Secrets of Men ſhall God then judg by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 2.16. (2.) Of their Matter; every good Work ſhall come in, the Feeding of Chriſt in his Hungry, the Clothing of him in his Naked, the Harboring him in his Deſolate, the Viſiting him in his Sick Members: and every Evil Work, not an ungodly Word nor hard Speech ſhall paſs, <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15.</p>
            <p>The other is 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33599:16"/>
it be Good or Bad.</hi> The things to be brought in, are the things done in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is to be underſtood not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively as if external Actions only ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but extenſively as including every thing we do while in the Fleſh, whether internal, even the naked Thoughts, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, Words and Actions. <hi>Omnia omnino opera quae fiunt dum vivimus in corpore, ſive interius nudis cogitationibus, ſive exterius ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; factis peragantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho I deſire as much as I may to decline Matters of Controverſy, yet here comes in a Query that I cannot well paſs over in Silence; it is this, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the Sins of the Saints ſhall be laid open and manifeſted at this Day? or whether the Books when opened ſhall open the Sins of the People of God, as well as the Sins of the Wicked? It is a Queſtion agitated among the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſome maintain the Affirmative, and ſay, they ſhall be made known: others are for the Negative, and ſay, they ſhall not be manifeſted. I'll only premiſe theſe three or four things, and with Submiſſion give my Thoughts about it in ſhort. The Sins of the Godly ſhall not be opened,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To their Condemnation; our Saviour himſelf ſays, Joh. 5.24. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, he that heareth my Word, and believeth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting Life, and ſhall not come into Condemnation. There is</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>no Condemnation to thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33599:17"/>
who are in Chriſt, who walk not after the Fleſh but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1. Nor yet,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To their Shame and Reproach; they ſhall not be produced to their Infamy or Diſgrace. Sinners riſe to everlaſting ſhame and contempt, but Saints to Glory, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. They may lift up their Face, and <hi>have boldneſs in the Day of Judgment,</hi> 1 John 4.17. Nor,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the abatement of their Joy in that Day. The appearance of their Sins in that Day of the Lord ſhall no more abate their Joy, than the appearing of the dead Carcaſes of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> on the Sea-ſhore did the Joy of the delivered <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Neither,</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the damping or diminiſhing of their Love to the Lord. If the Woman to whom many Sins were forgiven loved much, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.47. then the Saints ſhall not love God leſs, when they ſee how much hath been forgiven them.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things being thus premiſed, I ſay, I conceive it is probable that the Sins of the Saints ſhall be opened at this opening. I'll give you my Grounds for it, and leave it to that Day that will fully open this and other things yet in the dark.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Becauſe the Expreſſions concerning the Objects of this opening are Univerſal. The perſonal Objects are thus ſpoken of, Rom. 14.10. <hi>We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment-Seat of God.</hi> The real Objects
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33599:17"/>
are expreſs'd in the ſame Terms of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality, every thing, whether open or ſecret; every Work, whether good or evil, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. every Man, and every thing of every Man is to come to this open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Becauſe there is ſuch a Mixture of the Sins of many wicked and godly Men, that the Sins of the Wicked cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed with their ſeveral Circumſtances, and the Sins of the Godly remain cloſed, but if the one come fully out, the other muſt. Thoſe who are for the <hi>Negative,</hi> think the Strength of the former Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fully diſcharged by this Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Terms and Notes of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality in the Places mentioned are not to be taken collectively, as aſſerting that the Sins of the Godly as well as Ungodly ſhall be manifeſted, but diſtributively, thus, that the good Works only of the Good, and the evil Works of the Wicked, ſhall be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. But this Key will not (for ought I ſee) ſit all the Wards of that Lock. Yet they confeſs, that all the Works of wicked Men ſhall be proclaimed: Now many Sins of wicked and godly Men lie ſo mingled together, and are ſo concatenated ſeveral ways, that it's not eaſy to conceive how the Sins of the Wicked can be laid open, and the other not come out too. It's ſure a groſs Abuſe of Scripture, and a great Sin in wicked Men to juſtify and harden
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33599:18"/>
themſelves (as many have done) in Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, by the Example of <hi>Noah;</hi> in their cuſtomary Oaths, by the Example of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph;</hi> in Uncleanneſs, by the Example of <hi>David:</hi> but how can theſe Sins come out, and the Sin of <hi>Noah, Joſeph,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> not be made known? It was a Sin in the High-prieſt to grant Letters of Perſecution to <hi>Saul,</hi> Acts 9.1, 2. yet how can theſe Letters be produced but it will appear that <hi>Saul</hi> was once a Perſecutor? I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thee who art now a Convert to have been, when unregenerate, guilty of Folly and Lewdneſs with ſuch a Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the Perſon with whom thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittedſt it to have died in an impenitent State; how can that Party's Folly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and thine with whom it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted lie hid?</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Becauſe the blotting out of Sin is referred to this opening Day: <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your Sins may be blotted out when the Times of refreſhing come from the Preſence of the Lord.</hi> Here you have, 1. A Duty propoſed and preſs'd, <hi>Repent.</hi> 2. A Motive annexed, taken from the profitable Conſequent, <hi>that your Sins may be blotted out.</hi> 3. The Time when this Benefit is to be received and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, <hi>When the Times of refreſhing come from the Preſence of the Lord;</hi> at this open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day. The Scriptures ſpeak of a blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Sins at that Day, not but that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33599:18"/>
the Saints injoy a real blotting out of Sin before that Day; not that their Pardon of any Sin is not plenary, but imperfect, having part of its Guilt remaining then to be done away: but the Meaning is, that then they ſhall ſolemnly, openly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly before Men and Angels be cleared from every Charge of all accuſing Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and their Abſolution proclaimed before the World.</p>
            <p>Now this Blotting out implies ſome Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Sins from which they ſhall then be ſolemnly acquitted. This may be the Meaning of that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. <hi>It ſhall not be forgiven neither in this World, nor in the World to come; i. e.</hi> An Act of Pardon ſhall neither now be really paſſed, nor then ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly proclaimed, and by his declarato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sentence ratify'd. Sins that have been blotted out intentionally from Eternity in the Decree of God, and virtually from the Paſſion and Reſurrection of Chriſt by his Satisfaction, and formally or actually in themſelves from their Union to Chriſt, ſhall in this opening Day be publickly and ſolemnly blotted out to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Becauſe this ſeems to make much for the Illuſtration and Exaltation of the Grace and Glory of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. to manifeſt the glorious Effects of his Paſſion and Satisfaction: When it appears what Sins, how many, and how various have been laid at their Door, the Love,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33599:19"/>
Paſſion and Merits of Chriſt will be more elevated, Glory and Honour will redound on Chriſt; then it ſhall appear what Strength was in his Love, what Value in his Blood. I might yet further urge the opening of the Books; the impartial Manifeſtation of the Sins of Saints as well as others in the Holy Scriptures; the dangerous Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the contrary Tenent; the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation it will be to the Horror and Sting of the Reprobate, when they ſee others (that have ſinned alike in ſome things) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Glory, and themſelves for their Unbelief and Impenitence ſhut out. But the fore-mentioned are the Arguments that ſway moſt with me in this caſe. Now what remains but that we apply this Truth thus explained in thoſe Uſes that it gives us, which are of
<list>
                  <item>Information,</item>
                  <item>Reproof,</item>
                  <item>Exhortation?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Of Information: Shall the Books be opened? Then we may hence learn;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all our Actions are of a laſting Nature. Theſe die not in the Birth, but are abiding and for many Days to come. There are many things in this Life which as to the acting of them are tranſient and ſoon over, yet are durable in regard of their Iſſue. A Leaſe is writ over in two or three Hours, yet the Concernment of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33599:19"/>
it may be for many Years, yea for ſome Lives. So it is with our Thoughts, Words and Actions, they do not die as ſoon as they are paſt, but are as Seeds which are ſown in Time, and come up in Eternity: <hi>Non tranſeunt opera ſicut tranſire videntur, ſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut aeternitatis ſemina jaciuntur.</hi> There are Books of Remembrance, all is put on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that we do, and is in a ſort eternal. Says one, every Thought we think is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, every Word we ſpeak is eternal, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Work is eternal, none of theſe but ſhall live to this opening Day. O remember this Sirs! your Actions paſs not away, all that you do to Day, all that you ſhall do to Morrow, will remain till the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All that in any Place, on any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in any Company, proceeds from you, will tarry till this Day come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all our Actions muſt come to Light: They are not only laſting, but ſhall be opened. All thoſe things that have been covered in Darkneſs, that Men have acted under a Cloak, that no Eye but that which is all-ſeeing ever ſaw, ſhall come abroad. I remember a Story of <hi>Ottochus</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who refuſed to do Homage to the Emperor, till at laſt chaſtis'd with War, he was content to do it privately in a Tent, which Tent was ſo contrived by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Servants, that by drawing one Cord it was all taken away, and ſo the King was preſented on his Knees doing Homage to him in the view of three Armies then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33599:20"/>
preſent. That which he thought to have kept covered, was manifeſted before a great Number of Perſons. Thus will God at this Day uncaſe and lay open Mens Doings. There are many who care not what they do, ſo they can but do it ſecretly. O but this Cover ſhall be taken from over them, and they repreſented as doing ſuch and ſuch things before Armies, not only of Men, but Angels. <hi>There is nothing covered, that ſhall not be revealed; and hid, that ſhall not be known and come abroad,</hi> Mat. 10.26. Luke 8.17. <hi>Whatſoever ye have ſpoken in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall be heard in the Light; and that which ye have ſpoken in the Ear in Cloſets, ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed upon the Houſe-tops,</hi> Luke 12.3. Your moſt ſecret Talk and Communion one with another ſhall be made publick. All the Hypocriſy of Men ſhall be brought out; all their Guile and Fraud; all their Force and Violence they have uſed in their Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhall appear; all their By-ends they have had in any Action; all their vile and abominable Practices, of which I may ſay as the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.12. it is <hi>a Shame to mention them;</hi> even theſe that it's a Shame for Chriſtians to ſpeak of, ſhall be ſeen to their eternal Shame that have done them. As the Lord by <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.12. <hi>Thou didſt it ſecretly; but I will do this thing before all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and before the Sun:</hi> So may I ſay, You do this or that ſecretly, but the Lord will make it openly known.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33599:20"/>3. That we muſt meet all our Works again. All that ever we do in the Body now, we ſhall meet in the Books then. The things that now ſlip away from us, and we ſee them no more, will come again into our Sight when the Books are opened. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians tell us of ſome Rivers which after they have run ſome ſpace, fall under Ground and cannot be ſeen, but after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miles running in the Bowels of the Earth, they break up again into a great Stream. Thus the River <hi>Ana</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth it ſelf, and runneth under Ground fifteen Miles, and then comes up again, whereupon the Spaniards brag they have a Bridg on which ten thouſand Cattel feed daily. So there are many things we do which are no ſooner done, than we forget them, they paſs out of our Sight as Waters buried under the Earth. But every one of theſe after they have been a long time hid will come up again. Sirs, all that we do in this will meet us in the World to come. Our Sabbaths, our Duties, our Works will meet us, yea our Thoughts and Words will meet us. Art thou a God-fearing Man or Woman? all thy Goodneſs ſhall meet thee; not a Prayer, a Tear, a Sigh ſhall be miſſing, nor any thing that thou haſt done or ſuffered for God. Art thou a Perſon working Iniquity? Thy Works firſt and laſt, thy old and new-done Deeds will meet thee. Perhaps now thy Deeds of Darkneſs lie all aſleep, and make no Noiſe in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33599:21"/>
thy Conſcience. O, but at this day of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, theſe ſleepy Lions will awake and roar upon thee. Thy Oaths, thy Lies, thy Drunkenneſs, thy Worldlineſs, all thy Sins will then ſtare thee in the Face as ſo many Ghoſts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That we have need to be circumſpect and careful what we do at all times, and how we carry in our Generation, for there are many Notaries about us continually. God (as I may ſay) is ever writing, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ever writing, Devils and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ever writing. Nothing that we do eſcapes their Books, they take all at length to the laſt and leaſt Circumſtance of every Action and Work: what manner of Perſons then ought we to be? Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts tell us of ſome Kings, that tho other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would have taken more Liberty, yet they have been circumſpect in their Actings, becauſe they knew what they did would be regiſtred and tranſmitted to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. Did this ſo influence them? What Circumſpection ſhould it beget in us, when we ſeriouſly conſider that all we do will be regiſtred by many Hands, and certainly tranſmitted to Poſterity, and not only ſo, but to this great opening Day, where it ſhall be opened to all Generations that have gone before, or ſhall come after us to the end of the World? O think of it! It's ſaid of <hi>Apelles</hi> the famous Painter, that he carried on his Work very leiſurely: and being asked why he was ſo deliberate and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33599:21"/>
curious, his Anſwer was, <hi>Diu pingo, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam aeternitati pingo;</hi> 
               <q>I am long in paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe what I paint I paint for Eternity, <hi>q. d.</hi> I am thus exact becauſe not only the preſent, but many Ages to come are to look on and judg my Work.</q> Thus, Sirs, many Eyes, and many Ages to come are to look on and judg our daily Works and Ways, and all the Paſſages of our Lives. O therefore let this teach us to live for an opening Day; to be careful nothing now be writ but what we would have read then by the whole World of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men!</p>
            <p n="5">5. That this opening Day will be a great Day. 'Twill be a great thing to ſee all Mankind meeting together; all that ever have been, are, or ſhall be over the Face of the whole Earth, ſtanding in one Company before the ſupreme Judge. O, but will it not be much more to ſee all the Doings of all Men laid open! the Secrets that have been hid from Ages, and from Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, now made manifeſt! all the things that have been done in Darkneſs, and covered with as much Darkneſs as that wherein they were committed! O what, what a Day will this be? and what will many ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be when the Books are opened, and all the Paſſages of their Lives manifeſted! O what Heaps (as I may ſay) will there be here of Oaths, there of Lies, there of idle Words, there of Frauds, Sabbaths profaned, Sermons ſlighted, and of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33599:22"/>
Sins of all ſorts that Sinners have laid at their own Doors, and died impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in! Yea, what will many be found when the Books are opened, who have ſaid well, ſeemed well, done many things, and after all gone out of this World with the Applauſe of Men? Surely many who can now ſay much, ſpeak of God, and breathe out Good, will then be found others than at preſent they are taken to be. Secret Hypocriſy, ſecret Worldlineſs, ſecret E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangedneſs from the Truth and Power of Godlineſs, will then be found where now there's little Suſpicion of them. O that you would think of this, and ſee that you be indeed <hi>Nathaniels.</hi> There is in the Life of <hi>Bruno</hi> (Author of the Carthuſian Friars) a Relation of a great Doctor (and his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Profeſſor) a Man highly reputed in thoſe times both for Piety and Learning, who being dead, when they brought him to the Church to be buried, as they were about the Funeral-Rites, the dead Corps ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſat up upon the Bier, and cried out, <hi>Juſto Dei judicio accuſatus ſum,</hi> 
               <q>I am ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by the righteous Judgment of God, at which the People ran away amazed.</q> The next Day they came again to inter the Corps, and as they were about the Service, it roſe again and cried with a lamentable Voice, <hi>Juſto Dei judicio judicatus ſum,</hi> 
               <q>I am judged by the righteous Judgment of God.</q> The third Day almoſt all the City came together; and again it roſe up
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33599:22"/>
and with a doleful Noiſe cry'd, <hi>Juſto Dei judicio condemnatus ſum,</hi> 
               <q>I am condemn'd by the righteous Judgment of God.</q> That this was true I ſhall not aſſert; but certainly when the opening Day comes, many will be found in this caſe, many that have died in great Repute for Piety and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, will then ſtand accuſed, judged and condemned. Many a Face of Wickedneſs will then be unmasked that hath been co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Vail of Diſſimulation; many an unſound Heart will come out that hath been cloaked under ſpecious Performances; many a glorious Profeſſor will then be found a gilded Sepulchre. Sirs, look to, and ſee that you be altogether Chriſtians, for theſe Books will open all, and open that which will exclude many from the Kingdom of Heaven who have been great Preachers, great Profeſſors, that have known much, done much, gone far, and been well thought of by all round about them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it will then be in vain for Men to ſeek a Cover for their Sins. Our firſt Parents had no ſooner ſinned but they were for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, and this is natural to us their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerity; <hi>Job</hi> 24.15. <hi>The Eye of the Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer waiteth for the Twilight, ſaying, No Eye ſhall ſee me.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> that good Man had faln into the foul Sin of Uncleanneſs, you cannot, if you read the Hiſtory, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.) be ignorant what Means he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33599:23"/>
us'd to hide it. This is very uſual, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſays <hi>Job,</hi> ch. 31.33. <hi>If I covered my Tranſgreſſion as</hi> Adam, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſay ſome, as our firſt Father did, ſeeking to cloak his Tranſgreſſion: or as <hi>Adam, i. e.</hi> ſay others, as Man, as Man uſes to do, or after the manner of Men. But alas, this is a moſt vain Practice, for Sin cannot be covered from the Eye of God now; <hi>For there is no Darkneſs, neither Shadow of Death, where the Workers of Iniquity may hide themſelves,</hi> Job 34.22. for <hi>he ſetteth their Iniquities before him, their ſecret Sins in the Light of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> Pſal. 90.8. Nor ſhall they at laſt be hid from Men and Angels. This will be one ſpecial Work and End of this Opening to bring all Secrets to Light, to manifeſt the Counſels of the Heart. Of all Sins theſe ſhall not be covered, it's a Day appointed for the opening of theſe, therefore ſays the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Judg nothing before the Time, until the Lord come, who will bring to light the hidden things of Darkneſs.</hi> Why will God then judg them? The Meaning is not, that God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empts them from the Puniſhment of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtrates, reſerving them wholly to his own Judgment, but 'tis becauſe ſuch Sins are commonly ſo ſecretly committed, that the Magiſtrate cannot, or ſo lightly looked on, that he will not puniſh them; therefore God will at that day judg both thoſe things which have now been wrong
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33599:23"/>
judged, and thoſe which have not been judged at all. It's vain then to expect your Sins ſhall be covered, let not Hopes of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy embolden you to meddle with Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This opening will open Secrets, and theſe will bring moſt Shame on you, and do moſt harm to you. There have been many ſtrange Diſcoveries of ſecret Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in the World. 'Tis ſtoried of one <hi>Beſſus,</hi> that having killed his Father, he was ſo purſued with a guilty Conſcience, that he thought the Swallows as they flew about in their chattering ſaid, <hi>Beſſus</hi> hath killed his Father; whereupon he confeſſed the Fact.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That Shame ſhall come upon Sinners at this day, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. What the Lord ſpeaks of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> that will he do to all the Sons and Daughters of Wickedneſs at this day; <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>He will diſcover their Skirts upon their Face, and will ſhew the Nations their Nakedneſs, and the Kingdoms their Shame: he will caſt abominable Filth upon them, and make them vile, and will ſet them as a gazing Stock.</hi> O think of this Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and what Shame it will lay on you who go on in your Iniquities! Alas, were many of our Doings diſcovered now to a ſmall Aſſembly of People, how could we face them? ſurely it would make many to look with Faces like Death. How will it be then in this great Day, when all muſt be brought forth not in a Corner before a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33599:24"/>
handful, but in an open Place before a World!</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Terror and Aſtoniſhment that ſhall at this day fall upon Sinners. As it's ſaid of the Morning, that it is to ſecret Sinners <hi>even as the Shadow of Death,</hi> Job 24.17. So I may ſay, this Opening will be to them as the Terrors of the Shadow of Death. They ſhall not only, as the Thief, be aſhamed when he is found, but they ſhall be made a very <hi>Magormiſſabib.</hi> As the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> when he ſaw the Hand-writing on the Wall, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.5, 6. So they, when they ſhall ſee the Books opened, and what they have writtten in them, their Countenances will be changed, and their Thoughts troubled. O Sirs, it cannot now be conceived what Horror will then fall on ungodly Men. Have you ever ſeen poor Malefactors going with Death in their Faces to the Bar where they knew that Capital Crimes would be charged on, and undeniably proved againſt them? The Sight of theſe poor pale trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling diſpirited Creatures was nothing to that which ſhall be ſeen at this opening of the Books. When poor Sinners are come to this, to have all laid open, and can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deny any thing they have done, nor excuſe it, nor appeal to a higher Bar, what a pitiful taking will they be in? O that this might be thought on now in time e're it be too late!</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33599:24"/>9. That we had need to take care how we cloſe up our Days and die; for as we leave the Books at Death, juſt ſo we ſhall find them at this great Day of Judgment, when they muſt be opened. <hi>In quocunquè invenerit ſuus noviſſimus dies, in hoc eum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit mundi noviſſimus dies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Aug.</hi> 
               <q>In what ſtate our laſt Day (ſays he) finds us, in that will the laſt day of the World find us, for ſuch as we die in that Day, ſuch we ſhall be judged in this.</q> 
               <hi>Qualiſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hinc egreditur, talis in judicio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatur,</hi> Greog. <q>Such as we go hence (ſays he) ſuch we ſhall be preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God's Tribunal: He that goeth hence in his Sins ſhall be found in them.</q> Learn hence therefore to take heed how you venture on Death, what you leave written in the Books at your leaving the World. You would not die in Debt, leave Bills and Bonds behind you that may trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Poſterity when you are gone: beware of dying Impenitent, of leaving Sin on the Score; for this will, if ſo left, trouble you another Day, and undo you for ever.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That it is a bleſſed Thing to be a pardoned Sinner, to have Sin pardoned. O this is a choice favour. <hi>David</hi> marks the Man thus privileged, for the happy Man; he doth not aſcribe Bleſſedneſs to the Rich, to the Honourable, and Mighty of this World: It's not he that hath
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33599:25"/>
Health, Riches, Honour, and Friends, that is bleſſed becauſe he hath them; but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the Man <hi>whoſe Tranſgreſſion is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, whoſe Sin is covered,</hi> Pſal. 32.1. That this is ſuch a bleſſed Thing, ſuch a ſignal Mercy you may ſee from this Truth now under Conſideration. The Books muſt be opened: will it not then be a ſweet, a bleſſed Thing at this opening to find our Sins blotted out, to ſee a red Line of Chriſt's Blood drawn over them from end to end, ſo as we may ſtill ſee the Sum we were indebted in, but ſee it cancell d ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be expected? <hi>Arrow. Chain.</hi> p. 211. Thus it ſhall be with true Penitents at this Time; when others ſhall find all to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for, they ſhall ſee their Sins as the poor Man ſees his Debts in the Creditors Book, when either forgiven or paid, <hi>viz.</hi> croſſed out, and never to be charged on him again; thus they ſhall ſee all blotted out. And will not this be a bleſſed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege? Verily it will. I remember <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions mentions it as a ſweet Mercy that he could look the Sins of his unconverted State in the Face and not be afraid. Says he, <hi>Quid retribuam Domi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> quod recolit haec memoria mea, &amp; anima mea non metuit inde?</hi> Aug. Conf. l. 2. c. 7. <q>What ſhall I render unto the Lord, that my Memory can recollect theſe, and not be afraid?</q> Truly, Sirs, it is not now fully known, nor ſhall before the opening
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33599:25"/>
Day what a great Happineſs it will then be to be able to look on our Sins and not tremble, to look on them and not be at our wits end becauſe of them, as ungodly Sinners will then be, to whom it will be a greater Terror to meet their Sins, than now it is to meet ſo many roaring Lions.</p>
            <p>Second <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is of <hi>Reproof</hi> to thoſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who never think of this Day, nor how it ſhall then be with them. This is the Caſe of many ſecure and careleſs ones, who drive on in a ſtate and way of Sin from Day to Day, and take no Thought about this Opening that is coming upon them. It was once the complaint of a good Man, Alas, what do I mean? I eat, I drink, I play, I ſleep, as if I had gone behind Death, and paſſed over the Day of Judgment. It may more ſadly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of many, that they carry as if there were no ſuch Day to come, as if there never ſhould be any opening again of the things done in the Body; they take not this into their Thoughts. Many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily embrace <hi>Solomon</hi>'s ironical Conceſſion, (<hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9.) but they as willingly forget his ſerious Admonition, <hi>But know thou that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> this they have no mind to remember. Art thou of this ſort of Perſons? doſt thou never think of this Day? is it a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33599:26"/>
that hath no room in thy preſent Thoughts? There is ſuch a Day a coming, the Books ſhall be opened wherein all that you are doing Day after Day is recorded, ſhall be diſcovered, and tried, and there ſhall be a Manifeſtation, Teſtification, and Determination of all. You ſee this, and will you forget it? what Madneſs is it, and how ſad is it that you ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this! <hi>Auſtin</hi> compares ſuch careleſs Perſons to them who awake out of a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy, and fall into a Phrenſy. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if you go on at this rate, this Day will overtake you unawares, and then you are ſure to be awaked, awaked out of this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy of Security, and thence ſuddenly to paſs into a Phrenſy of everlaſting Horror and Aſtoniſhment. As it was in the Days of <hi>Noah,</hi> they were ſecure, and knew not till the Flood came: <hi>Noah</hi> had preached it to them, prepared the Ark before them, yet they took no notice of it; knowing they would not know till Deſtruction came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly on them: So ſhall it be in the Day of the Son of Man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.38, 39. This Opening will come on Sinners when they think not on it; and how ſad will it be to ſee all this on a ſudden, when there will be no way to eſcape, nor Time to prepare? O think on this, and let it at laſt put you on thinking that there is an opening Day to come!</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33599:26"/>2. To them who from Day to Day live in Sin and Ungodlineſs. They are not a few who are workers of Iniquity, that drive a Trade of Sin; how many may we meet with in every Place, and among all Ranks of Perſons that are plodding on in a Courſe of Vice? Open Profaneneſs is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very common in theſe Days. O the Profaneneſs, the Profaneneſs, the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Profaneneſs of our Towns and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations! who can look out with an Eye but half open, and not ſee Iniquity abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? which way can you turn and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thoſe Perſons who <hi>drink in Sin like Water,</hi> Job 15.16. who <hi>do Evil with both Hands,</hi> Mich. 7.3. and <hi>weary themſelves to commit Iniquity?</hi> Jer. 9.5. Debauchery is become a piece of Gallantry, and Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance a part of Religion, and open Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs an ordinary Practice with very many. Thus there are many every Day filling the Books with Pride, Oaths, Lies, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Uncleanneſs, Oppreſſion, Profaning of the Lord's Day, and many ſtrange Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations. But this Truth brings ſad News to all theſe if they would open their Ear to hear it; it tells them that there is an opening Day coming, wherein all theſe things muſt be opened again, and account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for. Conſider it, art thou an intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Perſon, living in Exceſs, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſtrong Drink? Or a cuſtomary Swearer, filling thy Mouth with Curſing,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33599:27"/>
or Bitterneſs? Art thou a filthy Adulterer or Fornicator, commiting Folly, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt thy own Body? Art thou a griping Oppreſſor, who inricheſt thy ſelf by making a Gain of the Neceſſity or Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of others, and bringing the Spoil of the Poor into thy Houſe? Art thou a fraudulent Perſon, reaching at all thou canſt come by, be it by Right or Wrong, never ſtanding to make uſe of Oaths and Lies, ſinful Subtilties, and ſecret Tricks in thy Trade, or ſleights in thy Dealings, ſo that thou mayſt but hook in ſomething thereby to thy ſelf? Or art thou a Man or Woman living in the Practice of any other mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and open, or ſecret and hidden Sin and Ungodlineſs? this Truth comes with aſtoniſhing Tidings to thee. Conſider it you that are of this ſort of Perſons, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are Atheiſts, or Mad, wholly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide your ſelves: Are you not Atheiſts? do you indeed believe this, that there will be an opening of the Books, and that ſuch an opening as will lay all open? Then ſurely you are diſtracted; for how can it otherwiſe be? How is it poſſible that Men believing ſuch a Day as this (if not beſide themſelves) ſhould live ſo profanely, ſince thereby they prepare themſelves to be then unavoidably and eternally deſtroyed? Can this be imagined to be the Work of any but diſtracted Perſons? certainly it cannot. How wiſe ſoever you may be in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33599:27"/>
your own Eyes, or in the Eyes of others like your ſelves, yet theſe are the Ways of Men void of Underſtanding. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knowing the Terrors of the Lord, how tremendous this Judgment will be, and what a terrible Time it will be with the Ungodly; I would earneſtly beſeech and beg of you to take theſe things into your ſerious Thoughts, that you may think of repenting and turning to God. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite you to this, conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. God hath revealed his Wrath from Heaven againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Men in his Threatnings, back'd with many ſad Examples in all Caſes, which are expoſed to your view, and left for your Warning. You are plainly told, that God <hi>will by no means clear the Guilty,</hi> Exod. 34.7. That <hi>the fooliſh (i. e.</hi> wicked Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) <hi>ſhall not ſtand in his ſight,</hi> Pſal. 5.5. That <hi>deſtruction is to the Wicked,</hi> Job 31.3. That <hi>the Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell,</hi> Pſal. 9.17. That <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9. <hi>The Angels that kept not their firſt ſtate,</hi> are <hi>reſerved in everlaſting Chains under Darkneſs, to the Judgment of the great Day.</hi> The old World did for Sin ſuffer a Deluge; for this <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were reduced to Aſhes; <hi>Iſrael</hi> were overthrown in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and many ſuch ſad Inſtances there are ſet forth to thoſe who after ſhould live ungodly, and written for our Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33599:28"/>
upon whom the ends of the World are come. Sirs, there's no way of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but you may find a word of Wo and Wrath revealed from Heaven againſt it; you cannot open your Bibles now but you are ready (if you had Eyes to ſee, and Ears to hear) to lighten and thunder Terror in your very Faces.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all your Ungodlineſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs againſt which God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed his Wrath from Heaven, is this Day book'd up, and on Record. Have you now been Drunkards, Fornicators, Oppreſſors, Worldlings for many Days? The Sins you have committed as ſuch are in the Books: as you have kept ſinning, God and Conſcience have kept writing, not one of all your evil Deeds, tho never ſo little or ſecret, hath eſcaped; but all are writ, and ſo writ that no Time can ever wear or waſh them out.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That you are bound over to an open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day, and muſt certainly and unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly come to it. <hi>There is a Day appointed in the which God will judg the World,</hi> Acts 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 30, 31. At this Day you muſt appear, there will be no eſcaping, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Kings and Potentates of the Earth, who can now beſt ſhift off Matters, ſhall then weary themſelves with vain Cries to the Rocks for ſhelter from the face of <hi>him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 6.15, 16, 17. All muſt appear at
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33599:28"/>
this great Audit, and grand Aſſizes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That you muſt meet there all your Doings in the Books, and find them fairly written in this opening Day. And, O Sirs, what a fearful Meeting? what a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sight will this be, when all your Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of many Days, Weeks, Months and Years, ſhall appear all together at once to you? This will be an appalling ſight. It's ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.12, 13. that when <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Cup was found in <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s Sack, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs rent their Clothes, they were aſtoniſhed, amazed, and ſtruck with Confuſion. If this did put them into ſuch a Poſture, O what rending of Hearts will there be at this Day among Sinners, when their Sacks, the Bags where their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions are ſealed up, and their Iniquities ſewed, are opened! O Sirs, it will be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to meet your Sins than now it is, they will then appear to you as ſo many Ghoſts. You converſe with living Men without fear, it never once troubles you to meet them in the Way, or in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, or to ſit with them in the Houſe. But if a Company of Dead Men ſhould come out of their Graves, meet you in the Way and purſue you, would not this affright and put you to a great Conſternation? Why the Sins that you now commit in the Way and Market, at your Bed and Board, will then meet you as ſo many dead Men, and be terrible to purpoſe. O remember
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33599:29"/>
this, Sin, Sin will be another thing when you meet it again in the Books, than now it is in your Eyes: There will be more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with reſpect to it 'tween now and then, than there is 'tween meeting a living Man you are well acquainted and intimate with, and meeting a Spirit in the likeneſs of a dead Man. Alas, Soul, all the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that thou canſt have in thy Sin, if thou mightſt live in it a thouſand Years, is not able to recompenſe thee for the Horror that this ſight will put thy Soul into; nay, if thou didſt but ſee one Sin now, as thou ſhalt then ſee all, thou wouldſt not chooſe to continue in Sin for the gaining of ten thouſand Worlds.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That you muſt have all that is in theſe Books, all your Deeds of Darkneſs, and Works of Iniquity laid fully open before God, Angels, and Men: as you cannot hide your ſelves, ſo you cannot hide any of your Sins. I would have you conſider, this Day there will be no hiding of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. No queſtion but as Men will be for crying to the Mountains and Rocks to hide themſelves, ſo they will be ſeeking where to hide their Sins that they may not come to light. A cruel <hi>Cain</hi> will then be for hiding his Brother's Blood; a Covetous <hi>Achan</hi> for hiding his Golden Wedg; an Oppreſſing <hi>Ahab</hi> for hiding his <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard; a Drunken <hi>Nabal</hi> for hiding his Vomit; the filthy Fornicator for hiding
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33599:29"/>
his Uncleanneſs. O where, where, will one cry, may I hide my Gain of Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Where, will another ſay, may I now hide my Tricks and Sleights that I raiſed my Eſtate by? Where, will a third cry, may I now hide my Lies and Oaths? O where may I hide my profaned Sabbaths, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent time of Grace, abuſed Seaſons of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation! Where may I hide this Sermon, and that Ordinance that are ready to riſe up and condemn me? Where may I, who have lived in a Time of great Goſpel-light, hide my Ignorance? O I would give all that I have for ſome where to hide theſe things ſo as they may never come to light. But all this will be in vain, there will be no Place to hide either your ſelves or Sin in.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That you muſt come to an Account and Reckoning for all. As all muſt out, ſo all muſt be accounted for, to the very laſt and leaſt <hi>idle Word,</hi> Matth. 12.36. You muſt be accountable for all the Evil you have committed, of all the Good you have omitted, of all the Talents you have been betruſted with, as Time, Health, Wealth, Goſpel, Sabbaths, Sermons, and Ordinances; all muſt be accounted for.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That as you muſt come to Account, ſo you can in no wiſe anſwer for what you have done. Alas, Sirs, your Doings, your Lies, your Oaths, your Drunkenneſs, will be unanſwerable Matters; all your witty
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33599:30"/>
Diſtinctions, Shifts and Excuſes will be of no Uſe when God ſhall ſay, Why have you done ſo and ſo? why were you drunk at ſuch a time, in ſuch a Place? why did you defraud one another? why did you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane my Day? I ſay, you'l then be ſilent. The Man who <hi>had not on the Wedding-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſpeechleſs,</hi> Matth. 22.12. This ſhows how little you can anſwer for Sin, how ſhiftleſs and ſpeechleſs Guilt will make you. O think on this, and let the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Unanſwerableneſs of your Doings put you to break from your ſinful Ways! And that the rather, becauſe as you cannot anſwer for them your ſelves, ſo,</p>
            <p n="8">8. There will be none to anſwer for you. Job 5.1. <hi>To which of the Saints wilt thou turn?</hi> Alas, it will be in vain to turn to any of them. None of them will anſwer in thy Behalf, nor can they if they would. Only Chriſt Jeſus can anſwer for Souls in this caſe; but if thou come to this Opening in thy Sins, he will not then anſwer for thee: <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. <hi>God hath now indeed exalted him with his right Hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give Repentance unto</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Forgiveneſs of Sins.</hi> But when this opening Day comes, it will be <hi>the great Day of his Wrath, and who ſhall be able to ſtand? Rev.</hi> 6.17. This will be a Day wherein he will not come to plead for them that are found in their Sins, but to render Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to them.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33599:30"/>9. You are ſure to be caſt and fall in the Judgment. This will be the Iſſue, you'l not be able to anſwer for your ſelves, Chriſt will not anſwer for you, God will abate you nothing, therefore ſurely you cannot <hi>ſtand,</hi> Pſal. 1.5. There are but two ways of Standing in the Judgment; either Firſt, by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Faith, and they who have this ſhall ſtand; <hi>For he that believeth on him is not condemned,</hi> John 3.18. <hi>He</hi> (ſays Chriſt) <hi>that heareth my Word, and believeth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting Life, and ſhall not come into Condemnation,</hi> John 5.24. Or, Secondly, by our own Righteouſneſs, or the Works of the Law, an abſolute and every way perfect Conformity to the Law; if a Man had this he might ſtand thereby. But now, Sirs, the Ungodly can ſtand nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two ways: Not by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, for they are Chriſtleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Not by their own Righteouſneſs, for they are Tranſgreſſors of that Law that curſes for the leaſt Breach thereof, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. This way of ſtanding is, and ever hath been impoſſible for all Mankind ſince the Fall. <hi>Therefore</hi> (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.) <hi>by the Deeds of the Law there ſhall be no Fleſh juſtified in his Sight.</hi> Therefore; wherefore? why, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>That every Mouth may be ſtopped, and all the World become guilty before God.</hi> This way the moſt eminent of Saints cannot ſtand;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33599:31"/>
Pſal. 130.3. <hi>If thou, Lord, ſhouldst mark Iniquities; O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?</hi> David himſelf ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>Enter not into Judgment with thy Servant: for in thy Sight ſhall no Man living be juſtified.</hi> Thus Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, you are ſure to fall in the Judgment, you have not Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and Man is not <hi>juſtified by the Works of the Law, Gal.</hi> 2.16. And,</p>
            <p n="10">10. If once you fall in Judgment, you muſt fall into Hell, where you muſt lie till you <hi>have paid the uttermoſt Farthing,</hi> Mat. 5.26. And when will that be? Why, never, the Puniſhment there will be <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> ch. 25.46. Your Damnation ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Damnation, becauſe you can never make Satisfaction. Well, Sirs, theſe are the things I would intreat you to take into your Thoughts, they are certain Truths: and will you yet continue in your ſinful States and ungodly Ways? Will you, tho you know that the Wrath of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from Heaven againſt all Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men? Will you, tho your Ungodlineſs and Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs be on Record? Will you, tho you be bound over to this opening Day, and muſt unavoidably come to it? Tho you muſt there meet all your Actings fairly writ in the Books? Tho all your Deeds of Darkneſs and wicked Works ſhall be fully diſplaid before God, Angels, and Men? Will you, tho you muſt come to a Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33599:31"/>
for all; tho you'l not be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for your ſelves, neither will there be any to anſwer for you? Will you, tho you are ſure to fall in Judgment, and to be caſt into Hell? Will you, I ſay, notwithſtanding all this, perſevere in Sin? Truly if this be your Reſolution, it's a ſad Reſolution. You are reſolved to damn your ſelves to all Eternity. But, O! if you knew but what Damnation is, if you had but once ſeen what's doing in another World, or but felt that one Hour which the Damned are groaning under, and have to groan under to Eternity, you would be of another Mind.</p>
            <p n="3">3d <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is of Exhortation:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> General, to all:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Particular,
<list>
                  <item>1. To Sinners.</item>
                  <item>2. To Saints.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> General, to all. Shall the Books be opened? Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Remember this Opening, and carry it on your Thoughts every day. This is the firſt Word I would leave with you. Think, O think much of this Day, this Day that never had the like before, nor ever ſhall again have after it! You have probably heard of that Saying, <hi>Whether I eat or drink, whether I wake or ſleep, methinks I hear that Voice ſounding in mine Ears, Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judgment;</hi> (Jerom.) Why ſo, Sirs, where-ever you are, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33599:32"/>
you do, let this Opening be in your Eye, and upon your Thoughts? Think on this when you go to Prayer: This Prayer, my Preparation for it, my Frame, Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and Ends in it, muſt all be opened another day. Think on this when you go to hear, this Sermon, every Truth and Duty laid before me herein will meet me again at the opening of the Books. Think on this when you have to do with others, to buy or ſell, or tranſact any Affairs about this Life with them. Theſe Actions I now do, and all the Circumſtances thereof will be found in the Books at the laſt Day. Think on this when Temptations come on you, and are in their Power, if now I yield, I give place to the Devil, and lay Sin at my door, and it will abide in the Books till they open, and all come out. And ſo in all other Caſes carry this along with you in your Thoughts. Pray read, hear, buy, ſell, eat and drink, and do all that ever you do as remembring this. Remember this Opening of the Books, Chriſtians; and let the Remembrance of it,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Be a Remedy againſt Sin, a Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative againſt Iniquity in theſe ſinful ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning times wherein Iniquity abounds. It's the Remedy that <hi>Solomon</hi> preſcribes to young Men, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9. and there is much Weight in it, if Perſons would but lay it to Heart. Remember, Sirs, when you are ready to turn into any Act or Way of Sin,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33599:32"/>
and let no Secrecy, no hope of hiding it from Neighbours, Friends, or the whole World incourage you to venture on it; for chooſe how you may now cover it, the Books will open it. Let no ſeeming Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of any Sin draw you to make light of it, for there is none ſo little but there will be room enough found for it in the Books. The Tradeſman hath not only a room in his Books for Pounds, Shillings and Pence, but alſo for Half-pence and Farthings, and will not leave out one, but put it in its place. So be ſure God hath a room in his Books for your leaſt Sins, which will coſt (ſays one) either the Blood of Chriſt or your own Ruine er'e they be wiped out. O remember that Sin goes out of your Thoughts, out of your Words, out of your Works and Ways into theſe Books that are ready to be opened before all the World. Watch therefore Temptations, watch carefully againſt Sin, againſt the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of Sin, and Appearance of Evil.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Let the Remembrance of this Day invite you to Repentance. <hi>Paul</hi> urges this as a forcible and preſſing Motive to this Duty, and tells us, that upon this Account God <hi>commands Men every where to repent, Acts</hi> 17.30, 31. Art thou an impenitent Sinner, one who haſt been and art back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the Thoughts of Repentance? be forward in Thoughts of this. O think what thou haſt in the Books already, how
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33599:33"/>
many things, and foul things are on Record againſt thee, how many Oaths that thou haſt ſworn, how many Lies that thou haſt told, how many vain and idle Words that thou haſt ſpoken, and how many ſinful and unlawful Deeds that thou haſt done. Take but up theſe Thoughts, and they'l convince thee of the need of Repentance, they'l in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thee to the Practice of it. The Books muſt be opened, how ſad will it be if they open on thee in an impenitent State! Art thou one who haſt laid the Foundation of Repentance from dead Works? May not this be a mighty Motive to thee to keep on building every day upon that Foundation? Thou reneweſt thy Sins every day, is there not then Cauſe every day to renew thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? Surely, Sirs, if you think of this Opening, and how you are ſinning, it may be enough to make you ſay as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſaid of himſelf, <hi>Nulli rei natus niſi poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae,</hi> that he was born for nothing but to repent. Saints ſhould not put more Sins in God's Book, than they put Tears in his Bottle.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Let it put you upon the Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Corruptions, and travelling af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deliverance from this Body of Sin. If your Sins be found alive at the opening of the Books, you muſt die. If they be not then dead, then your Life goes for them; for <hi>if ye live after the Fleſh, ye ſhall die, Rom.</hi> 8 13. And may not this put you on
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33599:33"/>
this Study? We find that when <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> had erected a golden Image with this Commination, That whoſoever would not fall down and worſhip it, ſhould be caſt alive into a firy Furnace, (<hi>Dan.</hi> 3.) that this took ſuch Impreſſion on all that heard it, that there were none except three or four which did not preſently fall down unto it: the Thoughts of a firy Furnace made them do any thing. God hath kindled a Fire that ſhall never be quenched; and when the Books open, all that have not thrown down their Corruptions, their Pride, Paſſions and Worldlineſs, ſhall be thrown into it without Exception. And may not the Thoughts of this be enough to ſet us upon throwing our Luſts down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us? It is ſaid of the Roman <hi>Cato,</hi> that for a long time he never declared his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about any Matter in the Senate, but he would ſtill cloſe with this Expreſſion, Methinks <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed: This ſat much on his Spirits. So truly if we look at this Opening, methinks this ſhould be on our Hearts, (whatſoever elſe we think or do) that our Corruptions ſhould be deſtroyed, the Fleſh with the Affections and Luſts mortify'd.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Let it quicken and engage you to Sincerity in your Profeſſions, Actions, Ends, Aims, and all that you do or ſay. The Welch have a Proverb, That it is hard to know three things, an Oak, a Day,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33599:34"/>
and a Man. An Oak, for the privy Wind and Shakes that may be within when it ſeems fair without. A Day for the Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Weather and Accidents. A Man, for his hollow Hypocriſy. Why, truly now it's hardly known who is a Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and who ſincere; who is really for God and Godlineſs, and who in Shew and Pretence only. <hi>One that is a Sheep without may be a Sow within.</hi> But, Sirs, make ſure to be what you ſeem to be, to do what you ſeem to do, to do that with your Heart that you do with your Hand. Let this Opening be an Antidote againſt Hypocriſy, carnal and corrupt Ends in Religion and Profeſſion. Harbour not an unſound Heart under fair Pretences, corrupt Ends under ſpecious Performances, or a made Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Life without Truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts. For the very Hearts muſt be ripp'd up and laid open at this Day, which will unmask and make naked all the <hi>Jehu's</hi> and <hi>Judaſſes</hi> in the World, the moſt cloſe and wily Hypocrites that ever were under Heaven. In our Life-time we have been judged by our ſelves and others with our Clothes on, then we ſhall all be judged naked, all Vizards ſhall be laid aſide. O remember, remember this Opening, and let it quicken you to Sincerity. <hi>Luther</hi> tells us of one <hi>Arſenius,</hi> who made a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, was a Man of eminent Parts, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſcourſing to Admiration; when
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33599:34"/>
he came to his ſick Bed his Friends that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited him expected to hear ſome great Matters from him, and told him, that ſure he could not but enjoy much Comfort who had been ſo eminent for the Profeſſion and Practice of Godlineſs. But he anſwered, that he had not that Comfort they thought he had, for he found it now with his Soul not according to what Man judgeth, but according to the Judgment God paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and God (ſaid he) judgeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment. Thus at this great opening Day it will be with us, not according to what we have only ſeem'd to be, or what others have conceiv'd of us, but according to what the great God really finds; and all will ſignify nothing if he find not Truth within.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Let it put you upon ſerious Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be entire and perfect in all Points and Parts of Religion, to fill up your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion in every part. O Sirs, be not partial in your Obedience, in with one, out with another Duty; careful in ſome things, careleſs in others! But make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of every known Duty, indulge not any one known Sin: tho you fail in every part of your Work, yet neglect not any part of it. Say not of any Duty as <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, In this, Lord, pardon thy Servant,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.18. Excuſe me, Lord, in this Neglect, in this Omiſſion, in this diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with my Duty, in this indulging of my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33599:35"/>
Sin. I ſay, omit not any part of Duty, for the Books muſt be opened; and when theſe are open, what hath been wanting will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; where our Profeſſion hath not been filled up, the Gaps and Chaſms will be found; ſuch an one was forward to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Duties, but was a prayerleſs Perſon, and had a prayerleſs Family; ſuch an one was much for Duties of the firſt Table, but little for Duties of the ſecond. The Books will open Omiſſions as well as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, and God (as one ſays) will judg you, and may condemn you for what you have not done. Not doing is Damning as well as ſinful Doing. You find in that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proceſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.42, 43. that what mention is there made is of Omiſſions, for not doing. He does not ſay you robbed me, you perſecuted me, you put me in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but ye gave me not Meat when I was hungry, ye did not take me in when I was a Stranger, nor viſit me when in Priſon. And this their not doing what they ſhould have done, was their undoing, and brought Damnation on them. <hi>Lavater</hi> in his Book of walking Spirits relates a Story concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Severinus,</hi> a renowned and famous Man in the times he lived in, who appeared when he was dead, and confeſſed that he was grievouſly puniſh'd becauſe he had not ſaid over his Canonical Hours in due time and diſtinctly, but had hudled them up in haſte. This is but a Fiction, yet certainly,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33599:35"/>
Sirs, there are many now in Hell for Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Let it induce you to Exactneſs in all your Works and Ways, not only to make Conſcience of every Duty, but to ſtudy to be exact therein. This Opening may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite to purſue <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Counſel, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy Hand findeth to do, do it with thy Might, i. e.</hi> to bring all thy Skill, and lay out all thy Strength in the doing of it. One drawing the Picture of <hi>Alexander</hi> while there was a Scar on his Face, drew him with his Finger upon the Scar to cover it. And <hi>Apelles</hi> painted another half-faced to cover the want of an Eye. But, Sirs, there are no ſuch Draughts of Perſons or Actions in theſe Books; there's no drawing of Perſons with Fingers upon Scars to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, no drawing of Actions half-faced to conceal Defects and Obliquities in them. They are all drawn fully as they are in themſelves: thy formal Duties will not be found half-faced to conceal the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of them; thy cold Performances will not be found half-faced, to cover their Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; nor thy uneven walking with Fingers upon the uncomely Haltings therein, to hide them. O methinks the Thoughts of this ſhould be a mighty Help againſt the too common Looſneſs of Chriſtians in their Spirits and Converſations, againſt the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, cold, remiſs and heartleſs Performance of Holy Duties!</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:33599:36"/>(7.) Let it be a Spur to Diligence, to Unweariedneſs in the Way, and abounding in the Work of the Lord. When <hi>Cornelius</hi> was praying, an Angel was ſent from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him with this Meſſage, <hi>Thy Prayers and thine Alms are come up for a Memorial before God,</hi> Acts 10.4. So Chriſtians, I am ſent with this Meſſage to you, to tell you that your Prayers and Alms, all your Works of Piety and Charity go up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and are put on Record in the Books that ſhall be open at the great Day; and may not this be a great Motive to preſent Diligence and Fruitfulneſs? Conſider, you ſhall meet all your layings out for God in the Books; your Tears, Prayers, Doings, Sufferings and Reproaches for Chriſt, ſhall be found when theſe open. There is a <hi>Book of Remembrance,</hi> Mal. 3.16. Chriſt will remember the feeding of him in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhing, the clothing of him in his Naked, the harbouring of him in his out-caſt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Cup of cold Water ſhall not be forgotten, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42. You ſhall at this Opening meet all your Layings out for Chriſt, and you ſhall alſo then meet the Reward of them all. It will be an Opening wherein the Judg will give <hi>Reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and to the Saints, and to them that fear his Name, ſmall and great,</hi> Rev. 11.18. God will <hi>render to every one according to their Deeds; to them who by patient Continuance in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33599:36"/>
Well-doing, ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality, Eternal Life,</hi> Rom. 2.6, 7. <hi>Therefore, my beloved Brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord, for as much as you know that your Labour is not in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1. Cor. 15.58.</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) Above all, let it put you to clear and evidence your Title to, and Intereſt in Chriſt. This was <hi>Paul</hi>'s great Ambition, to win Chriſt, and to be found in him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8, 9. O let it be your endeavour. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> tells us of a Univerſity where thoſe who were to proceed Doctor had certain hard Queſtions given them to reſolve, and four and twenty Hours allow'd them to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for their Anſwer; and according to the Reſolution they gave, they were either to receive their Degree with Honour, or to be ſent away with Shame. Sirs, when the Books are opened, this will be the great Queſtion to be reſolved, <hi>ſc.</hi> Whoſe are you? To whom do you belong? What Evidences can you ſhow? What Proofs can you bring of your Title to Chriſt? And according to the Reſolution you give of this, you muſt ſtand or fall for ever. O therefore ſtudy this Queſtion now, and ſee whether thoſe things you now bring as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of your Acquaintance with Chriſt, and Evidences of your Intereſt in him, be ſuch as will ſerve you to plead at this opening Day! Do you think that the bearing the Name of Chriſtians, the bare
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33599:37"/>
Profeſſion of Chriſt, your coming to, and ſitting under Ordinances, or your layings out in the performance of external Duties, are Evidences ſufficient of your Intereſt in Chriſt? If ſo, you are miſtaken; for Chriſt tells you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. That <hi>in that Day many will ſay, Lord, Lord, have we not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſi'd in thy Name, and in thy Name caſt out Devils, and in thy Name done many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Works? to whom he will profeſs, I never knew you.</hi> Nothing ſhort of ſpiritual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of Grace from him, and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him, will be enough to evidence an Intereſt in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Muſt the Books be opened? Then live for an opening Day, as thoſe that look for, and account that they muſt come to this Opening. It was the Orator's advice to his Hearers, <hi>Ita vivamus ut rationem nobis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendam arbitremur.</hi> Cicer. 4. in Verr. <q>Let us ſo live as thoſe that muſt give account of all.</q> It's the Apoſtle's Exhortation, James 2.12. <hi>So ſpeak ye, and ſo do, as they that ſhall be judged by the Law of Liberty,</hi> i.e. the Law that ſpareth none, but dealeth with all freely without reſpect of Perſons, though higher or richer than others. So ſpeak ye, and ſo do ye as thoſe that muſt come to the opening of the Books. Live now each Day as thoſe that are living for an opening Day; Live as you would be found to have lived when this Day comes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33599:37"/>(1.) In paſſing your precious Time that God puts into your Hand. Sirs, God takes notice what Time he gives every one of us, what we do with every Hour thereof, and will require it again at our Hands. O ſpend your Time as you would meet it at the laſt in the Books! Would you meet with empty Time, large ſhreds of Time that nothing has been done in? Would you meet with Time that hath been ſpent in vain Thoughts, waſted with idle Words, conſumed about Trifles and Impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? Would you meet with Days and Hours that have been ſpent in ſinful Sports and Recreations, as Carding, Dicing, Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Hunting, and the like Practices? Days and Nights that have been paſſed in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, Alehouſes, and Whorehouſes, in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, in Chambering and Wantonneſs? Would you then meet with Weeks and Years that have been loſt on your Luſts, one while on this Luſt, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while on that? Conſider this, would you meet Time thus ſpent, waſted, loſt, conſumed, at the opening of the Books? Sure you would not: but if you do, know of a certain that it will be a very ſad Meeting. As you would not thus meet it, take heed how you now ſpend it; for if you ſpend it after this manner, you muſt meet it ſo. But O carry as thoſe who are going to an opening Day, in placing and beſtowing your Time! So paſs your
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33599:38"/>
Time that you may be found to have lived long in a ſhort ſpace. It was the ſaying of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> That nothing is more amiable than well to place our Hours. This will certainly prove ſo, when the Books begin to open, and Time begins to come out (as it hath been paſt in ſecret) before all the World.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Live for this Opening in improving your Opportunities, your Days, and means of Grace; improve theſe as you would meet them in the Books. Will the Books bring any good News to you at their Opening, if then you be found to have waſted your Means and Helps that God gave you in order to Salvation, if Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities ſtand on Record, that you have neglected out of lazineſs, that you miſſed to gratify your Luſts, and that paſſed while you were paſſing your Time at drinking Matches? Would you meet Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths that have been ſpent in Recreations, Sermons that you have ſlept away, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances that you have been under, but made no uſe of? O, no, no! Therefore when Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities and Advantages are offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that you have liberty to cloſe with, think thus in your ſelves; Would I have it recorded in the Books that I miſt this Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, or that I made it not my Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to profit by it? See that you be ready to cloſe with, and diligent to improve Days and Means of Grace. Our Saviour came
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33599:38"/>
from <hi>Nazareth</hi> to <hi>Bethabara</hi> to be baptized of <hi>John, Mat.</hi> 3.13. <hi>John</hi> 1.28. which ſome compute to be fifty ſix of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Miles. But O, our lazineſs, who will not now go a fourth part of that way to partake of Ordinances? I have read of a good Man, who when his time for Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came, what Company ſoever was with him, would take his leave of them, with this fair Excuſe, he had a Friend that ſtaid to ſpeak with him, he meant his God. But, alas, how little Matters do we ſuffer to be Avocations and Interruptions? Any thing will ſerve many for an excuſe to ſhift off an Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Live for this Day in performing of Duties, as Prayer, Reading and Hearing the Word; perform theſe as you would meet them again. Would you meet cold, heartleſs, cuſtomary, overly Duties, Duties that your Hearts have not been in, Duties that you have run over without Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Intention? It will be but a poor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to meet a Company of theſe; and yet what ſad Work do many make this way! There are many (ſays Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi>) that will not omit Prayer; they pray from Day to Day, from Time to Time; and yet tho they pray every Day, they make not a Prayer all their Life, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Life or Power in their Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they only do them of Courſe, or in a curſory Way. O, Chriſtians, beware of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33599:39"/>
this, beware of Miſcarriages in your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; when Formality, Deadneſs, Sleepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wandrings creep on you, think how you can meet, face, and own thoſe Duties, thoſe Duties at the opening of the Books: carry theſe Thoughts with you as often as you go to any Duty publick or private.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Live for it in the Affairs and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your particular Callings; learn to manage the Buſineſs of your ſeveral Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and go through all your worldly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments on ſuch a manner as you would meet them again at this opening. Think how you would be found then to have gone through all your Matters, with what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, Plainneſs, Simplicity, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and ſtudy now to go through them on ſuch a manner: keep your Hands clean; keep your Hearts above the World, when your Hands are in it; Buy not under-Foot, ſell not at over-Rates; fetch not your Gain out of others certain and apparent Loſs; be not all for your ſelves without reſpect to their Indemnity with whom you have to do; uſe not falſe Weights, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or Lights; take not in any of thoſe numberleſs Tricks that all Trades are full of; reſolve either to be rich with Truth, or poor with Content. That paſſage of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, in a Letter to the late King <hi>Charles, viz.</hi> Do not think any thing worth obtaining by foul and unjuſt Means, was of great Weight with me when
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33599:39"/>
I firſt read it, and is worthy to be written in Letters of Gold. There is nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven worth obtaining by theſe means, or that being thus obtained, will bear its coſt, or prove a ſaving Bargain when the opening and accounting Day comes. O do nothing in your Callings and Affairs in the World that you would not meet at laſt! You would not meet the Tears and Cries of thoſe that you have wronged, the poor ſunken Families that you have oppreſſed, the Widows, or Fatherleſs, whoſe Land-marks you have removed. O, do no ſuch things as theſe now; or if any of you have done, make Reſtitution, make Reſtitution, otherwiſe ye will (as Father <hi>Latimer</hi> in his laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, ſaid to the Kings Officers) cough in Hell, that all the Devils there will laugh at your Coughing.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Live for this great Day, in order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole of your Converſation in the World; walk ſo as you would meet your ways again; let your Lives be uniform and all of one piece. It is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.17. <hi>Be thou in the Fear of the Lord all the Day long.</hi> If you would for an opening Day practiſe this, be in the Fear of the Lord all the Day, and every Day; let to morrow be as this Day, and the next Day as to morrow. There are ſome,<note place="margin">Gurn. <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 138.</note> if you would ſee their Goodneſs, and be acquainted with their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33599:40"/>
Godlineſs, you muſt hit the right Time, or elſe you will find none; like ſome Flowers that are ſeen but ſome Months in the Year; or like ſome Phyſicians that they call Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon Men, they that would ſpeak with them to any purpoſe muſt come in the Morning, becauſe commonly they are drunk in the Afternoon. Thus may be in the Morning you may take the Hypocrite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Knee in the Saints Poſture; but when that fit is over, you ſhall ſee little of God in all his Ways, till Night brings him again of courſe to the like Duty. Thus, Sirs, too many are of different and contrary Tempers; changes of Time, of Place and Company, make ſtrange alterations in their Frames and Carriages. As it is ſaid of the Women in <hi>Italy,</hi> that they are Saints in the Church, Goats in the Garden, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in the Houſe, Angels in the Streets: ſo it is with many, you may ſee them Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at one Time, Curſing, or Swearing, or Lying at another Time; Serious in one Place, Light and Vain in another; Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and for Religious Exerciſes in one Company, but Ranting, and Drinking, and Healthing in another; carrying as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in ſome Things, as Infidels or Atheiſts in other Things. But ſuch Carriages as theſe will not ſerve for an opening Day; they are ſad now, and a great reproach to Religion; but however any of you make them ſerve now, they'll never ſerve the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33599:40"/>
turn when the Books are opened: for our Actions and Carriages of all Times, Places, and Companies muſt be put in the Books, one as well as another; not only what we have done at ſuch a Time, in ſuch a Place, among ſuch Company when in our better Moods, but alſo what we have done at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Time, Place, and Company, when we were in a worſe Frame: If thou pray in the Morning, and drink and live looſely all the Day, and yet come to thy Knees again at Night, theſe things ſhall be pieced and put together juſt as thou haſt acted them; but ſuch Mixtures will make mighty bad work for an opening Day, it will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal to find the Books thus writ over: Here a Bible in the Hand, and next a pair of Cards or Dice; here on thy Knees in thy Family, next drunk in the Street or Tavern; here taking a turn in God's way, next walking in Sins way: Books thus written will open terribly. If you would live for this opening, you muſt ſtudy an oneneſs and equality of Carriage, and be <hi>Holy in all manner of Converſation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15. not in ſome turnings of your Life, but in your whole Courſe; you muſt do <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs at all Times,</hi> Pſal. 106.3. one and another without Exception. If we Ride, <hi>Holineſs unto the Lord</hi> ſhould be writ on our Bridles; if we Drink, <hi>Holineſs unto the Lord of Hoſts</hi> ſhould be upon our Pots, <hi>Zecha.</hi> 14.20, 21.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33599:41"/>(6.) Live for this opening, in laying out your Receivings, and imploying all your Talents the right way, whether Spiritual Graces, or Temporal Bleſſings. We find in the Parable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.14.—30. that the Servants who were entruſted with Talents were called to a Reckoning at laſt. This is that you muſt come to, the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire from you an account of your Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip. Would you live for an opening, an accounting Day? lay out your Talents in a right manner. Hath God betruſted you with a Talent of Grace, or Gifts, or Wealth, or Authority? Take heed what uſe you put them to, endeavour in your Place, and to your Power to profit others by them; uſe your Gifts and Graces in Comforting, Exhorting and Counſelling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Have you Wealth and Eſtates? think what good you may do with it. It's lamentable to ſee what uſe many that have uſeful Eſtates are making of them! One hath a fair Talent, in this reſpect, but he laps it up in his Napkin; the Church hath no help, the Poor fare no better, no good Work goes on faſter for him. Another hath the like Talent, and he uſes it, but how? Why, as Beaſts do their Horns, in acts of Violence and Oppreſſion: through Uſury and pinching Bargains he ſucks the Blood, and eats the Fleſh of many poor Neighbours about him, thriving as People on the Sea-Coaſts, by the Wrecks of Ships.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33599:41"/>
Another ſort waſte their Eſtates in Riot and Exceſs, in Surfeiting and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in Pleaſures and Paſtimes. <q>Were theſe to be painted, (ſays <hi>Baines</hi> on the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> p. 552.) they muſt be brought in with Dogs, Hawks, Dice, Cards, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans, not clothing the Naked, not feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hungry, nor converting any of their Eſtate to any good Uſe.</q> But what will theſe do when the opening and reckoning Day comes? O beware of ſuch Practices! And whatever God betruſts you with, be it more or leſs, make now the Uſe of it that you would be found to have made when the Books are opened. This the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Word, remember it, and remember to practiſe it. O, look on your Actions every Day, and think with your ſelves, will this and this ſerve for an opening Day, will this do at the great Aſſizes? Would I meet my Time thus ſpent, my Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thus entertained, Duties thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, Buſineſs thus tranſacted, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations thus ordered, Talents thus imploy'd at the opening Day? Will theſe Prayers, theſe Performances, theſe Bargains, theſe Ways do in that Day? Thus commune with your ſelves, and live as thoſe that muſt come to the opening of the Books.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Shall there be an opening of the Books? then prepare and get ready for it. Make it your Work Night and Day to get into a Readineſs for a comfortable meeting of this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33599:42"/>
great opening Day, be perſwaded to this whatever you leave undone. For conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That this Opening will come; you do but hear of it now, but you ſhall ſee it hereafter. As our Saviour ſpeaks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.64. <hi>Hereafter ſhall ye ſee the Son of Man ſitting on the right Hand of Power, and coming in the Clouds of Heaven;</hi> ſo may I ſay, Now you ſee but his poor Ambaſſadors that preach his Coming, but you ſhall hereafter ſee him come in a State of Glory to open the Books, to judg the Quick and Dead in one Day. Sirs, it is not a doubtful, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Point, not a Matter in Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy among Chriſtians, but a Principle owned and acknowledged by all Sides and Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, being as fully and clearly revealed as any thing in the Scriptures. The Apoſtle in that one Place, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. doth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently and notably ſet forth this grand Fundamental, giving us Account, 1ſt. That a Day is ſet, <hi>He hath appointed a Day: and the Counſel of the Lord ſtandeth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 33.11. The Decree is gone, the Day is proclaimed, it cannot be reverſed, but muſt and will moſt certainly hold. 2dly. Of the End of this Day appointed, <hi>viz. to judg.</hi> 3dly. The Object of this Judgment, <hi>the World.</hi> 4thly. The manner how this Judgment ſhall be managed, <hi>in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> there ſhall be no Corruption in this Adminiſtration. 5thly. The Judg, <hi>the Man whom he hath ordained, i. e.</hi> the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33599:42"/>
Chriſt, God-Man. 6thly. The Aſſurance hereof given unto all Men, in that he hath <hi>raiſed him from the Dead.</hi> This is ſufficient Teſtimony to convince all Men. This may be Inducement to the propoſed Duty of Preparation, there will be an opening Day. If it were a Matter only probable, if as much might be ſaid againſt it as for it, then Careleſneſs in preparing for it might be ſomewhat excuſable: But this is out of Queſtion, 'tis beyond all Diſpute, ſhall we not then make it our Work to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare? Conſider it, Sirs, God hath iſſued out a Proclamation, and it hath been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed again and again in your Hearing, wherein he gives you notice of a Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for this end, of the Perſons that muſt come to it, and that your ſelves are of this Number; ſhall you not then be moſt inexcuſable if you come to it unready? What will you ſay? Will you plead, Lord, had I ever thought of ſuch a Day as this, I would not have done as I have, I would have watched and prayed, and lived for it all my Days? Why, alas, thy Mouth will be ſtopped, Chriſt will tell you his Writ was out, and this grand Aſſizes was many a time proclaimed in thy Preſence; yea, the Books ſhall openly ſhow the Times, the Places and Circumſtances of its Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation to thee. O Sirs, the End is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared from the beginning, <hi>and from anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times the things that are not yet done,</hi> Iſa.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33599:43"/>
46.10. All Generations have had fair warning of it, and we upon whom the Ends of the World are come want none.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That the Time of this great Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is uncertain. The Opening is certain, but the Time when is unſeen. There have ſome indeed undertaken to foretel the Time. In the Primitive Days, and while the Apoſtles were yet alive, there were ſome that pretended Revelations or Viſions from the Spirit, declaring this Day to be then near, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. And ſince many have preſumed to foretel the Year, whoſe Predictions Time hath already confuted. <hi>Aventinus</hi> ſhows, that about the Year 1062. the credulous People were ſo deluded by ſuch ridiculous Predictions, that there was a general Expectation of the Great Day of Judgment as then juſt upon them. The furious Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the Year 1530, were ſo confident that the Laſt Day ſhould be within that Year, that ſome of them gave their Eſtates about them to thoſe who would have part, reckoning that a little would ſerve them for ſo ſhort a time; and ſome of them ran up and down, crying to the People with a doleful Noiſe, Repent, repent, the Day of the Lord is come, the Day of the Lord is come. There are ſome who told us, that the Year 1675, others that the Year 1680, others that 1688, others that 1695, and ſome tell us that 1700 will put an end to the World,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33599:43"/>
and open the great opening Day. But our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. aſſerts, that it is an unknown Day, 1ſt. To all Men, to the greateſt, the wiſeſt, the beſt of Men. No Man whoſoever, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, can tell when this ſhall be. 2dly. To all Angels; not only to us poor Men on Earth, but alſo to the glorious Angels in Heaven, who ſee the Face of God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Theſe, tho they muſt accompany Chriſt, tho they muſt miniſter to him in that Day, gathering all Nations before him, yet of this Day they know not. 3dly. To the Son of Man himſelf, as Man, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his humane Nature; for here he oppoſes himſelf as Man, to his Father as God. Or, the Son of Man knows it not with reſpect of his Office, tho he knew it with reſpect of his Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> he was not ſent to reveal and make this known to Man in his Miniſtry. Thus you ſee this Great Day is an unknown Day, a Day that ſhall come upon Men when they think not of it. Therefore he illuſtrates it by the coming of a <hi>Thief in the Night,</hi> Mat. 24.43. of a <hi>Bridegroom coming at Midnight,</hi> ch. 25.6. of a <hi>Maſter returning,</hi> Luke 12.36, 37. O this Day will come unawares upon the World: and doth not this call upon you to be ſerious in your Preparation for it! May it come this Night, the next Morning, when we are taking our Reſt? May we be awaked with this dreadful
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33599:44"/>
Sound, Ariſe and come to Judgment? or when we riſe and are abroad about our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, may we ſee Chriſt breaking out of Heaven, and coming in the Clouds with Power and great Glory? Why then we have need to make it our Work to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare. Our Saviour uſes this very Motive to perſwade to this Duty, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.44. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.40. In both theſe Places you have the Duty I am preſſing preſcribed, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ye alſo ready,</hi> ready to meet the Son of Man, ready to come to this opening Day. Alſo the Motive inducing thereto annexed, drawn from the Secrecy and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the Time; for in <hi>ſuch an Hour as you think not, the Son of Man cometh.</hi> They might ſay, Lord, but what need is there of all this, of getting into and keeping in Readineſs? will it not be time enough to do this when we ſee the Day approaching? what muſt we needs do it now? Yes, now be ready.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That this opening Day will be a great Day. As it will come, and its Coming is uncertain, ſo it will be a very great Day when it comes. The Apoſtle ſtiles it, <hi>the great and notable Day of the Lord,</hi> Acts 2.20. Obſerve, it's the Day of the Lord: theſe are our Days in which we eat and drink, marry and give in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and go over great Numbers and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of Actions; but this Day will be the Lord's Day, the Day that hath his Mark
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33599:44"/>
on it, as a Day whereon he will do his great Works. And it's the great and notable Day of the Lord: he hath had many Days of particular Rewards and Puniſhments, but no Day like this, therefore it's fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the Scripture called, <hi>That Day,</hi> by way of Excellency, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.8. that ſingular Day that never had any like before, or ſhall have after it; that wonderful Day; that laſt Day; that Day that ends all Days; that that all muſt come to; that Day that all ſhould prepare for; that Day that will be glorious to Chriſt; that Day that will be joyful to Saints; that Day that will be ſhameful to Sinners. Sirs, this Day, this Day of Days, will be a great and notable Day, if we conſider, 1ſt. The Perſon that ſhall then appear, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: It's call'd <hi>the Coming of our Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.7. <hi>The Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.7. <hi>The Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. He came once humbled in the Form of a Servant, but he ſhall then appear and be revealed in Glory, this will be <hi>the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Tit. 2.13. who ſhall come in a bright Cloud, <hi>in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body,</hi> Phil. 3.21. in <hi>his own Glory,</hi> Mat. 25.31. in <hi>his Father's Glory,</hi> ch. 16.27. in the <hi>Glory of his Angels,</hi> Luke 9.26. <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Thouſands miniſtring unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtanding before
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33599:45"/>
him,</hi> Dan. 7.10. O Sirs, the Coming of Chriſt at this Day will be a glorious Coming, he'll come in Glory and Power beyond all that e're was ſeen to this Day, and paſt all that e're ſhall be ſeen before that Day.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The Perſons that muſt come to this Opening. Many Thouſands, many Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, infinite Millions of Perſons, of all Ranks and Conditions. All Men, all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, all the World muſt be convened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him at that Day, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, 32. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. Not only Men, but Nations of Men; not only Nations, but all Nations, all the World. O what a Wonder will it be to ſee all Perſons that ever lived in all Ages of the World, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into one Company and Place!</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. The things that muſt then be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. All things of all Men, things that have been hid from Ages and Generations, things that were never opened before to any, ſhall come out then before all Men. There is nothing ſo ſmall or inconſiderable but will be revealed, nothing ſo ſecret or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den but it ſhall come abroad when the Lord comes, <hi>who both will bring to light the bidden things of Darkneſs, and will make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the Counſels of the Heart,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.5. And what a great Opening will this be? It will be ſuch a Sight as never was ſeen, to ſee all Mankind meeting; O but it will be more to ſee all things that have been
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33599:45"/>
done under the Sun by ſo many Millions of Men and Women brought and laid open as they are in themſelves, and their ſeveral Circumſtances!</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. The Greatneſs of the Aſſembly before whom the Books ſhall be opened. This Opening ſhall not be in the Preſence of ſome few, as of a Family, a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Pariſh, but in the Preſence of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men, before a World. Alas, many, many would be aſhamed to be laid open before a few of their Neighbours, and to have their ſecret things of Darkneſs brought out into Light among their near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Friends. O but Sinner, thoſe things at this Opening ſhall be opened before the World, that now thou wouldſt not have thy own Father to know, thy Mother that bare thee to ſee, thy Husband or Wife that lies in thy Boſom privy to, that Child that came out of thy Loins acquainted with, nor thy Boſom-Friend a Witneſs of.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. The things done at this Opening. Now at this Opening of this Grand Aſſize there will be a final Determination of all Mens States thence forward to all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. You have <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, 32. deſcribed the Preparatives to this Opening, <hi>viz.</hi> the Coming of the Judg, his ſitting on the Throne of his Glory, the Congregating of all Nations, their Separation one from another, the Collocation of the Sheep on his right, and the Goats on his left Hand;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33599:46"/>
and then you have the great Work of this Day, which lies mainly in paſſing a defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Sentence upon Perſons. There have been many great Trials here among Men, ſome have had Trials about Eſtates and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to Inheritance, ſome have got and ſome have loſt Eſtates of Hundreds and Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the Year: many have been upon Trial for their Lives, ſome ſtood, others faln. But all theſe, even thoſe of them that gave occaſion to the greateſt Noiſe in the World, are inconſiderable, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Cauſes to be determined at that Day. Then the Trial will be what Title Men have, not to ſuch and ſuch Houſes and Eſtates, but to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; what they can ſay, not to preſerve a temporal, but what they can ſhow for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; and he Determination thereof will not ſettle them in, or throw them out of temporal Poſſeſſions, but either ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a Kingdom on them to Eternity, or ſink them into a Priſon for evermore. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum momentum aeternam manſionem unicuique aſſignabit.</hi> Ger. Then one Moment will aſſign an eternal Manſion to every Perſon. Thus you ſee this Opening will be a great and notable Day, and may not this put you upon preparing for it! Suppoſe thou wert to have a Trial about thy Eſtate in the World, or wert to be tried for thy Life the next Term or Aſſizes, and the Cauſe were then to be determined with or againſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33599:46"/>
thee, wouldſt thou make no Proviſion for it, take no care about it? Surely thou wouldſt. We ſee Lawyers are thronged to in ſuch Caſes, Friends improved to the utmoſt, all Circumſtances weighed, and nothing neglected that may help. Why, thou art ſure at this Opening either to get or loſe a Kingdom, either to be made or undone, and that for evermore. O then fall upon this Work, and that the rather, becauſe,</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) This opening Day (wherein ſuch great things are to be done) will find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unready, and take many unprepared for it. This great Day will meet many with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing to meet it with. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2, 3, ſhows, 1ſt. How this Day will come upon the World, <hi>as a Thief, i. e.</hi> ſuddenly and unexpectedly; a Thief gives no Warning. 2dly. How it would find the World, <hi>viz.</hi> ſecure, fearleſs, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, unready, ſo unready that Deſtruction ſhall come upon them, and they ſhall not eſcape. Our Saviour himſelf (<hi>Luke</hi> 17.26-31.) ſets out this Day by comparing it with the Days of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood, <hi>q. d.</hi> there ſhall be a great Conformity 'tween thoſe Days and theſe, 'tween the Men of thoſe Times and theſe. How was it in the Days of <hi>Noah?</hi> they had heard of a Flood, (as we do of this opening Day) but they eat and drank (as we do) and never mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, till it came upon their Heads, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33599:47"/>
ſwept them all away. Why, even thus ſhall it be in the Day when the Son of Man is revealed. Many had heard of the Flood, but when it came few were in any Readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for it, or found any way of Eſcape from it: So, many hear of this Day, few will be found in Readineſs for it, and none ſhall eſcape it; and may not this awake you to Care in this Behalf! O many, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, many will be then unready! look to it that you be not of their Number, and that the rather, becauſe,</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) As you are then found, ſo you are ſure to fare for ever. Chriſt will take you juſt as he finds you at that Day. The old World was taken unready, and there was no Remedy, it was too late to think of preparing Arks. The fooliſh Virgins were found unready, and the Door was ſhut againſt them. So when Chriſt comes, poor Sinners that are found unready ſhall have no Time to provide in, he'l take them as he finds them, without any Delay. Some ſhall be found in the <hi>Bed,</hi> others in the <hi>Mill,</hi> others in the <hi>Field,</hi> Luke 17.34, 35, 36. and as they are found, ſo they ſhall be taken. If two be in one Bed, one a gracious, the other a graceleſs Perſon, they muſt immediately be ſunder'd, the one ſhall be taken to receive a Sentence of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, the other left to lie and ſink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Sentence of Damnation. The main Scope of this Diſcourſe is to ſhow that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33599:47"/>
there will be no coming off, no mending of Matters, no making of things either bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or worſe than they are found at that Day, but all Men ſhall be dealt with as they are found, and differently, according to their different States. O Sirs, when it's come to this, that the Books are opened, there will then be no further Tranſaction about Matters of Salvation or Damnation, but the Cauſe will be preſently and clearly determined either with or againſt you. Doth it not then concern every one to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get into a Readineſs for this Day?</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) That this Opening will be very dreadful to them that are unready. Many will be found unready, every one muſt ſtand as he is then found, and this Day will be terrible to thoſe on whom it comes in this Caſe. We read of three terrible Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: One when the <hi>Fountains of the great Deep were broken up, and the Windows of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were opened,</hi> Gen. 7.11, 21, 22, 23. Theſe were opened and never ſhut till the World was drown'd. Another is the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Earth which cloſed not again till it had incloſed <hi>Korah</hi> and thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to him, with their Houſes and Goods in its Womb. The third is the opening of the Cave at <hi>Makkedah,</hi> which uſhered in a ſpeedy Deſtruction to thoſe Kings that were a little before in great Pomp and State, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.22, 23. Ay but Sirs, this is a more dreadful Opening than
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33599:48"/>
any of theſe, and will be more terrible in it ſelf, and to them that come to it unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, than thoſe were. When the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven were opened, the World was drowned e're they ſhut again; but when the Books are opened, the World of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Men ſhall be damned e're they ſhut: When the Earth opened, it ſhut not again till it had ſwallowed up <hi>Korah</hi> and his wicked Accomplices: When the Books are opened, the Wicked ſhall ſink into Hell before they be cloſed again. When the Cave was opened, <hi>Joſhua</hi> took thence the five Kings, and cauſed the Captains of his Men of War to tread on their Necks, and afterwards ſmote them; but when the Books ſhall be opened, the Saints ſhall tread down the Wicked, and they ſhall be as Aſhes under their Feet. Heb. 10.31. <hi>It is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the living God,</hi> ſo as the Wicked ſhall fall. Pray think of it, it will be more Terrible than can now be expreſſed or imagined, all the Deſcriptions and Circumſtances of it (with reference to Men in their Sins) are very dreadful. As in a word or two to inſtance, this Day will be dreadful unto Sinners if we look,</p>
            <p n="1">1. At the Judg, who is deſcribed <hi>deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Heaven with a Shout, with the Voice of the Arch-angel, and with the Trump of God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.16. deſcending <hi>with his mighty Angels,</hi> accompanied <hi>with flaming Fire, to take
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33599:48"/>
Vengeance,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.7, 8. Pſal. 50.3. Mal. 4.1. to <hi>tear,</hi> Pſal. 50.22. to <hi>puniſh,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1.9. Theſe are tremendous Expreſſions, and if it be nothing to hear them, it will be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſee them receiving their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, to ſee Chriſt deſcending with a Shout, attended with his mighty Angels, clothed in Flames of Fire, to tear, take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and puniſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At the Day, which is ſet out on the like terrible manner, as <hi>a great Day,</hi> Jude 6. as <hi>a great Day of Wrath,</hi> Rev. 6.17. as <hi>the Day of Wrath and Revelation of the righteous Judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2.5. as <hi>the Day of Judgment and Perdition of ungodly Men,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.7. O what appalling Expreſſions!</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will be a terrible Day, if we look at the poor Sinners who are brought in <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wailing</hi> at the firſt opening of this Day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. Rev. 1.7. O then poor Scoffers, <hi>who walking after their own Luſts,</hi> (2 Pet. 3.3, 4.) <hi>ſay, Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</hi> ſhall have their Tune turned; They will then turn to their deſperate but bootleſs Shifts. When they ſee him on the Throne, they ſhall cry to the Rocks and Mountains, <hi>fall on us, and hide us from the Face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 6.16. But this will be a vain Cry; vain, I ſay, for the Creature cannot hide when the Creator is in purſuit. But tho this be in vain, they'll thus cry, which ſhows the Terror that ſhall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33599:49"/>
then come upon them. And if the ſeeing of the Judg make them thus a <hi>Magormiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bib,</hi> what a taking will they be in when the Books are opening, to open all their doings before the whole World? What a taking will they be in when the Damnator's Sentence is ringing in their Ears? when they are ſinking together into the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone?</p>
            <p n="4">4. At the Sentence to be paſſed on them, which is <hi>Triſtiſſima &amp; Horribiliſſima,</hi> moſt Sad and Horrible; <hi>Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 25.41. Every word carries a Wo, a thouſand Woes, a World of Woes in it. O Sirs, to depart, to be ſent away, to depart Curſed under the Load and Weight of Heaven's Curſe; to depart curſed from Chriſt the Fountain of Light, the Lord of Glory, and the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Pleaſures; to depart thence into Fire, into everlaſting Fire, Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels; this will be a fearful Thing! O when poor Creatures ſee that there is no eſcaping, but now they muſt go, and go with a Curſe for their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and go from Chriſt, Angels, Saints, and Heaven; and go to dwell in everlaſting Fire, and have the Devil and his Angels for their Companions; what Weeping and Wailing will there be among them?</p>
            <p n="5">5. If we look at the Conſequents of this Opening, theſe are very dreadful: for this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33599:49"/>
Opening will be immediately followed,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. With an Eternal Opening: (1.) Of Conſcience, which will cauſe reſtleſs and endleſs Terror, Horror, and Torment: (2.) Of the bottomleſs Pit, and Lake of Fire, where they ſhall be for ever torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with everlaſting Puniſhment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. An everlaſting ſhutting; (1.) Out of the Preſence of God, and Kingdom of Heaven: (2.) In Darkneſs, and under Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſay, how may we get into ſuch a readineſs for this great Opening of the Books, as that they may not open to our Shame, Confuſion, and Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Why, if you would be ready ſo as that when the Books open, Heaven may not ſhut, and Hell open on you to all Eternity, then,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Be often thinking on this opening Day; ſpend ſome time every Day in ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thoughts of this great Day. I have before preſſed this as a Duty incumbent upon all, and now urge it as a Direction for thoſe who would be ready at this Day. Wouldſt thou be prepared? then let this Day be ever in thy Eye by ſerious Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: this will be a good help unto thee in ſeveral Reſpects, as have been before ſhown. O therefore carry, carry this Opening ever in thine Eye! When thou openeſt a Book to read, or ſeeſt another open one, let it put thee in mind of this Opening of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33599:50"/>
the Books: When thou ſeeſt the Morning opening after a dark Night, and bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to light that lay covered with Darkneſs; let it put thee on thinking what an Opening there will be in the Morning of the Reſurrection and final Judgment, how things will then come out. When thou ſeeſt the Day ſhutting, think what a ſhutting this great Day will have. When thou art undreſſing thy ſelf, and putting off thy Clothes, think what a Day this will be when thou and all the Sons of Men muſt be ſtrip'd and laid open before the World of Angels and Men. When thou heareſt of ſtrange diſcoveries of Thefts, Murders, and Whoredoms, let it mind thee of this Opening that will open all the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of Darkneſs, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World to the end thereof; let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing be thus a Remembrancer to thee of this, and ſet afoot in thee ſome Thoughts about it. I have read of one of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients (noted for his ſingular Piety, and eminent Holineſs) who being asked what Books he made his Companions, and uſed moſt, he anſwered, that it was his Practice every Day to read over a Book that had three Leaves, one Red, a ſecond Black, a third White, <hi>Liber cujus tria folia, rubrum, nigrum, &amp; candidum.</hi> In the Red he uſed to read and meditate on the bloody Paſſion of Chriſt; in the Black, the Darkneſs and Damnation of Hell; in the White, the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33599:50"/>
Light and Glory of Heaven, whereby he gained more in the way of practical God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, than by any other ſtudy. I would here add a fourth Leaf to this Book, <hi>viz.</hi> This opening Day, and commend the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to every one that would be then ready.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Watch and Pray. This is our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Direction that he preſcribes in this Caſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. In the foregoing Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes you have, (1.) Our Saviour's deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Day. (2.) His admonition to his Diſciples, not to be <hi>taken unawares</hi> and unready, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. (3.) The Reaſon of this Admonition, <hi>For as a Snare ſhall it come on them that dwell on the Face of the whole Earth,</hi> Ver. 35. It ſhall come ſuddenly and take them unready. And then (4.) In theſe words you have his means of prevention pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and they are two, Watch, and Pray. Would you not be taken unready? Watch, exerciſe your ſelves in a univerſal Careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs over your Hearts and Ways, over the Wiles and Ways of Satan, over the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and motions of Corruptions in your ſelves, the Occaſions and Advantages of Sin in the World, that you fall not into Snares. And to Watchfulneſs join Prayer, that great ſafeguarding Duty. Watch and Pray, Pray and Watch, that ye may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy: Never think that you
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33599:51"/>
can be ready at this Day, if now in your Day you live at large, if you make no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what Company you walk with, what Temptations you run into, what Sins you lay at your Door; if you'll be falſe with God in your Profeſſion, unjuſt with Men in your Dealings; if you'll Drink and Swear, and Profane the Lord's Day: no, no, this work will not do; I tell you, Sirs, it will not do: Wo to you if any of you put it to this venture, and ſay, (as, alas, the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of too many ſay aloud) either this ſhall do, or I'll be undone, for then you are ſure to be undone for ever. If you would have this Day find you ready, let to day and to morrow, and the next Day find you Praying and Watching, find you with your Loins girt, and your Lights burning, as Servants that wait for their Lord. We read of <hi>four Beaſts,</hi> Rev. 4.6, 8. that were full of Eyes, both before, and behind, and within. Why thus, as theſe had not one but many Eyes, ſo you muſt be full of Eyes; there muſt be Eyes looking forward, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ever what we have before us, what we enter on, or put our Hand to; and there muſt be Eyes looking backwards, ever reflecting on paſt Actions, on what we have done, that we may ſpy and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our Errors; and there muſt be Eyes looking inward, watching over that cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deceitful Piece the Heart, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33599:51"/>
the workings thereof. They that would be ready at this Day, muſt Watch and Pray at their Day.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Make the Word of God the Rule of your Converſation in the World: This muſt be the Rule of Judgment then, let it be the Rule of your Life now; you muſt be judged by this Book at the great Opening (if you would then ſtand) live by it now in your Day. This is another thing I would leave with you by way of Direction, O take it up! You ſee there muſt be a great Opening, Men muſt be judged accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Works, and their Works according to the Word; ſo that if you would be ready, live now according to this Book, and learn to walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Rule, in all your Ways and Actions keep an Eye on this. We find that the four Beaſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8. had each of them ſix Wings about him, and they were full of Eyes within: Wings are for Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Eyes for guidance and direction in that Motion; ſo that this Phraſe imports that their Motion was not blind and lawleſs, but regular and orderly. Why thus we muſt have Eyes under our Wings, <hi>i. e.</hi> our Actions and Motions muſt be ordered, guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and directed by the Light of the Word: ſays <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.105. <hi>Thy Word is a Lamp unto my Feet, and a Light unto my Path;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33599:52"/>
q. d.</hi> I am as one in the dark who dare not walk, nor ſtir a ſtep from his Station with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Light to direct him. I dare not walk without thy Word, turn into any Way and Courſe but ſuch as this guides me into, and ſhines on me in. So he ſhows that God's <hi>Teſtimonies were his Counſellors,</hi> ver. 24. He alludes unto the Cuſtoms of Kings who have their Counſellors ever ready to aſſiſt them in their great and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous Affairs, <hi>q. d.</hi> As Kings have their Counſellors, ſo have I too; thy Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they are the Men of my Counſel, in all my Matters I go to them, and conſult with them, I hear what they ſay, and of them I take Direction. Why thus, Sirs, if you would be in readineſs for an open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day, let the Word of God be a Lamp to your Feet, and let his Teſtimonies be the Men of your Counſel; e're you enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or take in Thoughts, before you ſend out any Words, or ſet upon any Actions, go to this Word with them, and hear what it hath to ſay of this Thought, that Word, of thoſe Works, and let it be your utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour as far as is poſſible, to put nothing into thoſe Books which ſhall be opened, but what this Book now open warrants and allows. If ſuch and ſuch an Action, Way, or Practice, will not ſtand before the Word, let it not ſtand in your Lives, this is the Way to ſee a comfortable opening at laſt. <hi>Si
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33599:52"/>
hunc librum Conſcientiae recte vis ſcribere, ſcribe eum ſecundum exemplar libri vitae; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vitae eſt Chriſtus,</hi> &amp;c. <q>If you will write the Book of Conſcience aright, write it according to the Book of Life; the Book of Life is Chriſt.</q> Let the profeſſion of your Faith be conformable to the Rule of his Doctrine, and in your Life imitate the Life of Chriſt. <hi>Every one that doeth Evil hateth Light, neither cometh to the Light, leſt his Deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> John 3.20. They cannot abide to be tried by Scripture-Rules, they dare not put their Doing to be tried by the Book of God; but this will make foul work for an open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Day. If your Ways cannot ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Word now, never think that they ſhall ſtand before it another Day: The Word that now condemns Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will then condemn it; the Word that condemns Oaths and Lies now, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them at that Day. The Sentence at this great Opening ſhall not be another, or different Sentence, but only a Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Confirmation of that which is now paſſed in the Word upon Men and their Actions. O if we would but make it our Care to follow this one Direction, and write nothing in thoſe Books which are to be opened, but what we take out of the Book which is now open and ſet before us as our Exemplar and Copy, putting nothing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33599:53"/>
on record there but what we find allowed here; then what manner of Perſons ſhould we be, and how far otherwiſe would the Books be found at this great Opening, than moſt muſt find them?</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Reckon often with your ſelves, call your ſelves frequently to account, be much in ſelf-examining, ſelf-judging Exerciſes. I have read of one who would ask himſelf three Queſtions every Night; (1.) What Evil haſt thou healed to Day? (2.) What Corruption haſt thou ſtood againſt to Day? (3.) Wherein, or in what art thou bettered now this Day is gone? Why on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Sirs, be often dealing with your ſelves, lay the Word and your own Hearts, the Word and your own Ways together at the end of every Day. When you have gone over a Day in the World, go over it again between the Word and your own Souls, and ſeriouſly renew your Repentance and Self-accuſations. You ſay, Often reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning keeps long Friends; O reckon oft with God and your own Souls; for <hi>if we would judg our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31. Our ſelf-accuſations would prevent Satan's Accuſations againſt us: He is the Accuſer of the Brethren, and will have many things to charge us with: but when a Man accuſes and humbles himſelf, Satan is prevented; tho he come in with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33599:53"/>
this and the other complaint, God will ſay (as it were) Why Satan, this Man hath accuſed himſelf before thou cameſt; thou art here with this now, but he was here with it and mourned over it as ſoon as it was done, the ſame Day; and he hath been oft at my Feet about it with Sorrow in his Heart, and Tears in his Eyes; yea this would not only prevent Satan's Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, but the Judgment of God. <hi>Judicio poenitentiali evacuatur judicium poenale.</hi> Amaſ. <q>If we would judg our ſelves with a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitential, the Penal Judgment would be prevented.</q> Says <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 32.5. <hi>I acknowledged my Sin unto thee, and mine Iniquity have I not hid; I ſaid I will confeſs my Tranſgreſſions unto the Lord, and thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaveſt the iniquity of my Sin.</hi> The Spouſe privy to her own Infirmities, called her ſelf black, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5. but Chriſt calls her fair. If we will condemn our ſelves, God will juſtify us; if we put out our Tears that come from a right Spring into his Bottel, he will not ſeal up our Iniquities (for which thoſe Tears were ſhed) in a Bag.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Make it your great ſtudy and care to have and keep Conſcience your Friend: this is now your conſtant Companion, and goes whither you go; this will be a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Witneſſes, yea, and a Judg in your own Boſom at that Day. Exerciſe your
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33599:54"/>
ſelf as <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>have always a Conſcience void of Offence toward God, and toward Men,</hi> Acts 24.16. Labour to have ſuch a Conſcience as may ſpeak well of thee when thou comeſt to Judgment. <hi>In die judicii plus valebit Conſcientia pura quam marſupla plena.</hi> Bern. <q>In the Day of Judgment a good Conſcience will be better than a full Purſe; for which many Men wound and wrong, and waſte their own Conſciences.</q> This will in that Day be no better than Mire in the Streets; but to have a good Conſcience go with us to the Bar, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for us there, will be ſomething. As you would ſtand in the Judgment, look to this in all your Ways, and be often liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear what it ſays to you, and of you. It's ſaid of <hi>Apelles</hi> the famous Painter, that when he had finiſhed a Draught, he would uſually expoſe it to view, and lie behind it, that he might hear what others ſaid of it. Why, on this manner bring all your Actions to the view of Conſcience, and hear what this (going by a right Rule, and rightly informed) ſays of them; for <hi>if our Heart condemn us, God is greater than our Heart, and knoweth all things,</hi> 1 John 3.20. This is but the Deputy-Judg, and if this condemn, the great and ſupreme Judg will not abſolve. Art thou forced now to neglect and diſregard, to ſilence and ſlight; nay, to wound and reſiſt thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33599:54"/>
would it ſtop thee, and thou wilt not be ſtopped? Why, alas, the Day is coming when this Conſcience will ſurely condemn thee, and God who is greater than Conſcience will condemn thee. Sirs, if you would have Conſcience your Friend at that Day, give it Content now; if you would not have it full of Complaints then, ſtudy to keep it void of Offence now.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Laſtly, above all, and without which all is nothing, labour to be found in Chriſt at this great opening Day. This was <hi>Paul</hi>'s great Study to win Chriſt, and <hi>to be found in him,</hi> Phil. 3.9. Let it be your great Buſineſs to win Chriſt againſt this Day, to be found in him at that Day. I ſay, to be found in Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be waſhed in his Blood, clothed with his Righteouſneſs, all lies on this, nothing but this will ſerve at this Opening. It's only Chriſt's Blood that blots, ſcores, and croſſes out our Sins; it's only Chriſt's Merits that ſatisfy divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for our Iniquities; it's only Chriſt's Righteouſneſs that covers all our Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and is our Righteouſneſs; it's on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt's Death that ſets Matters right between God and Souls intereſted therein. Nothing but Chriſt's Righteouſneſs will ſerve for Chriſt's Judgment. O when he comes with his Garments white as Snow, and Hair of his Head like the pure Wool,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33599:55"/>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9. and ſits on a white Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. there will be no ſtanding for any but ſuch as are arrayed in the white Robes of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs. Out of Chriſt then, and undone for ever; but if then you have Chriſt, all ſhall be well. <hi>Luther,</hi> in his Commentary on <hi>Geneſis,</hi> preſcribes unto tempted Perſons one compendious way to withſtand all Temptations whatſoever: ſays he, Let Satan come any way, or the World come any way, or the Fleſh move any way, anſwer all with theſe two Words, I may not, I muſt not, for I am a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Why, as that is a compendious way of anſwering all Temptations; ſo this will be a compendious way of anſwering all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers and Accuſations at the opening Day; and not only compendious, but the one and only way, <hi>viz.</hi> I have a Chriſt. As a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever may anſwer all preſent Temptations, ſo may he with this (when all is open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World, Angels and Men) anſwer all Accuſations of Juſtice, Law, Sin, Satan, and all Accuſers. It's called the Anſwer of a good Conſcience. A good Conſcience is a Conſcience ſprinkled with the Blood of Jeſus, and this Conſcience hath an Anſwer to make for the Soul. We read of the <hi>Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. Now an Anſwer ſuppoſeth a Queſtion, an Anſwer towards God ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a Queſtion from him to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33599:55"/>
Now the Queſtion (ſays one) that God is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to propound to the poor Creature,<note place="margin">Gurn. Chr. Arm. <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 334.</note> may be conceived to be this, What canſt thou ſay (who art a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſtands by the Curſe of my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Law, doomed to Death and Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) why thou ſhouldſt not die the Death pronounced againſt every Sinner? This is the grand Queſtion. Now, ſaith he, the Soul that hath heard of Chriſt, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him hath received him by Faith into his Heart, is the Perſon, and the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that can anſwer this Queſtion ſo as to ſatisfy God or himſelf. Take the Anſwer as it is formed and fitted for, yea put into the Mouth of every Believer by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.34. <hi>Who is he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right Hand of God, who alſo maketh Interceſſion for us.</hi> Who condemneth? Here is the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Interrogatory of a good Conſcience. It is Chriſt that died, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here's its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Anſwer, an Anſwer that none can ever object againſt. Why, my Beloved, as this is now an Anſwer beyond Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo it will be in that great Day. If you have but then this Anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and can ſay, I have a Chriſt who died for me, you ſhall need to fear no Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, no Condemnation. Even then when
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33599:56"/>
the Heavens and the Earth are flying away from the Face of him that ſits on the Throne, and Multitudes of all Ranks are crying to the Rocks and Mountains to fall on them and hide them from his Face, this Plea will abide the Sight of God, and ſtand before his dreadful Tribunal at the great Day of the Revelation of his righteous Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> Particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,
<list>
                  <item>To Sinners.</item>
                  <item>To Saints.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To Sinners. Shall the Books be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Then this ſpeaks to poor ſecure Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who make nothing of this great Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never mind it nor once think how they ſhall ſpeed at that Day; but ſay in their Hearts, If we may eſcape till then, then let us do as we can, we hope we ſhall ſhift as well as many more that will be in our own caſe. 'Tis to be feared that in theſe profane Times there are more than a few of theſe, who yet (led with Cuſtom) come to and ſet up their Faces in our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: If any of you that are come hither this Day be of this ſort of Perſons, ſuch as care not for this great Opening, but keep on in your Sins, filling up the Books every Day with new Abominations, the Lord hath ſent me hither this Day to meet you with a Word of Exhortation; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33599:56"/>
the Terror of the Lord, (what a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time it will be) I perſwade, beſeech, entreat you to entertain it. It's that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your Sins may be blotted out when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the Preſence of the Lord.</hi> This wrought with many at that time, <hi>ch.</hi> 4.4. O do no more make light of this Day and the things thereof, but repent now, and be convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that your Sins may be then blotted out. This is the Word that I would leave with you; and pray conſider, that you may not make light of it,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That Pagans and Heathens have trembled at the Hearing of this Day, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. Mark, <hi>Paul</hi> was here preaching, and <hi>Felix</hi> was hearing, and as <hi>Paul</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned he trembled, he was in a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Metu perculſus, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>territus:</hi> When the Judgment to come was laid before him, his Conſcience began to awake, and put him into a trembling Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. Now will you be worſe than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Pagans, more ſtupid, ſenſeleſs and fearleſs than Heathens? Shall a Man who never heard of a Day of Judgment before, who never was under an Ordinance before, (as <hi>Felix</hi>) tremble at the preaching of this Judgment, and you who have heard hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Sermons, make light of it? O
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33599:57"/>
think of this, and what a dreadful thing it will be to have a <hi>Felix</hi> riſe up in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you; poor Pagans to come in and cry, O if we had been forewarned of ſuch a Day as theſe have been, we would never have done as we did! Sirs, you would take it ill now if one ſhould rank you with Pagans and Heathens: O what, what will it be to be made ſpeechleſs by them, to have them crying and coming in againſt you; yea, to ſee the Lord himſelf bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them againſt you, and ſaying, Lo here are poor Creatures that would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented in Duſt and Aſhes if this Day might have been preached to them as it hath been many a time, and by many of my Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to you!</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That the very Devils themſelves tremble at the Thoughts of this great Day. They are reſerved in everlaſting Chains under Darkneſs unto the Judgment of the great Day, <hi>Jude</hi> 6. A Metaphor taken from notorious Malefactors who are kept in cloſe Priſon till the Aſſize where they are to be tried and have Judgment: Thus the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils are reſerved to this great Day, and they tremble to think of it. <hi>They believe and tremble, i. e.</hi> are under a continual Fear and Dread of the great God who will come one Day, as they know, to Judgment againſt them. This they tremble at: the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33599:57"/>
word ſignifies an extreme Fear, ſhaking and Tumult, as is in the Sea when it works and is tempeſtuous. Thus the Thoughts of the Day of Judgment make a Hurry, a Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even among the Devils, they are under dreadful Commotions at the Reflection on this Day, becauſe then the Fulneſs of their Torments are to begin. Hence was that Cry, <hi>What have we to do with thee, thou Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, thou Son of God? Art thou come hither to torment us before the time?</hi> Mat. 8.29. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> thinks that when the Devils ſaw Chriſt thus come into the World, they thought the Day of Judgment (which they expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not ſo ſoon) was juſt upon them, and this Apprehenſion put them into a mighty Conſternation: <hi>Art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi> O they were in a fearful Fit upon this. And Sirs, will you be worſe than the Devils, not only worſe than Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans but than Devils alſo? Will not that that ſhakes Hell it ſelf, ſhake and awake your Conſciences? Shall Devils tremble in Hell at the Thoughts of this Day, and poor Sinners on Earth (that muſt be in that Day ſorted, and ſink for ever with them) be ſecure and careleſs!</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That this Day will make you (that are moſt ſecure and confident) to tremble if it take you in your Sins: Pagans have trembled, Devils do tremble, and you ſhall
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33599:58"/>
tremble. <hi>The Wicked is reſerved to the Day of Deſtruction; they ſhall be brought forth to the Day of Wrath,</hi> Job 21.30. 2 Pet. 2.9. And O when this Day is come, and is upon you, there will be Trembling and Shaking amongſt you. The great Executions of Wrath on wicked Men are reſerved to that Day. There have been many terrible Plagues upon the World, but Sirs, the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, the ſtrangeſt, the moſt affrighting, have been but as Drops to the Showers of this Day, Smoakings of God's Wrath to the Fire of this Day. The old World was drowned with a very terrible Inundation, but there's a more dreadful Doom abiding for it. <hi>Sodom</hi> was deſtroyed with a ſudden ſtrange Deſtruction, but there's a more ſtrange Deſtruction to come on thoſe filthy Sodomites: <hi>Sodomiti olim perditi, iterum perdendi.</hi> Some of the Antients have ſaid, that there are three ſorts of Thunderbolts in Heaven; the firſt to warn, not to hurt; the ſecond to hurt, but not to deſtroy; the third to ruine and lay all waſte. The two firſt ſorts (ſays one) God often in this Life diſchargeth upon wicked Men, but the third and worſt is reſerved for this Day, when all the Artilleries of Heaven ſhall go off at once, when all the Fountains of God's Wrath ſhall be broken up, when the Lord <hi>ſhall rain Snares, Fire and Brimſtone, and a horrible Tempeſt</hi> upon the Wicked, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 11.6.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33599:58"/>
O Sirs, the Chear will be turned when you ſee Signs in the Sun, when you ſee the Tribes of the Earth mourn, the Heavens paſſing away with a great Noiſe, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments melting with fervent Heat, and the Earth with the Works that are therein burnt up. I remember I have read of crook-back'd <hi>Richard,</hi> that in that Battel wherein he fell, when he ſaw himſelf in a helpleſs Condition, he cried out vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>A Kingdom for a Horſe, a Kingdom for a Horſe.</hi> Why ſo, Soul, when thou art un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Circumſtances, thou'lt cry out, Riches for a Chriſt, Gold and Silver for a Chriſt, Houſes and Land for a Chriſt, a Kingdom if I had it for Chriſt, the World if it were mine for Chriſt. Now give me Chriſt, and Grace, and Pardon, and take all my Riches, Treaſures and Pleaſures; give me, give me theſe now, or I am for ever, for ever undone; I know not what to do, whither to go: God is againſt me, Conſcience againſt me, Satan againſt me, Fellow-Sinners are againſt me, Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, Creatures againſt me, the Law and Sin againſt me. Sirs, it will come to this with you; and when it is once come to this, there will be no eſcaping.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shall the Books be opened? Then it ſpeaks to the Saints and Servants of God, who have made it their Buſineſs to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33599:59"/>
to live for and be in a Readineſs againſt it, look for and comfort your ſelves with the Hope of this great Opening Day. Our Saviour ſpeaking of the Tokens of this Day, (<hi>Luke</hi> 21.28.) ſays to his Diſciples, <hi>Look up, and lift up your Heads, for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh, q. d.</hi> it ſhall be a good Day to you, you ſhall have no Cauſe to be diſmay'd, but may meet it with Comfort. It's obſervable, that this Promiſe is the laſt Promiſe in the Book of God, the laſt Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that Chriſt in Heaven ſends to his Church on Earth before his Coming again; <hi>Surely I come quickly,</hi> Rev. 22.20. with which, as good News, he cloſes all up, and you have its Welcome, <hi>Amen, even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi> O Sirs, the Saints have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, have comforted themſelves with the Hopes of this Day. <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, he had rather never have been born than not to be in Expectation of this Day. O it is a Day to be expected, a Day to be looked and longed for, and a Day to be rejoiced in! Conſider, that you may be quickned to look and long for it, to incourage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your ſelves in it,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That at this great Opening your Sins will be found blotted out. Thoſe Sins that you have gone mourning under here, that you have been under diſquieting Fears about, that have coſt you many Tears and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33599:59"/>
many waking Hours, will then all appear blotted out, ſtand fully cancelled, never to be required, and what a ſweet welcome Sight will this be!</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) At this great Opening your Names will be found written in the Lamb's Book of Life. Your Names ſhall be found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Heaven, and you ſhall fully ſee that you are the Objects of free, ſpecial, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing and diſtinguiſhing Love, reaching from everlaſting to everlaſting; and will not this be a bleſſed Sight?</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) At this Opening, the Face of God and Chriſt ſhall open on you, never to ſhut in or go under any Cloud again for ever. Here the Saints are abſent from the Lord, and the Lord is abſent from them in regard of the Smiles of his Face; but then they ſhall be for ever with him, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) At this Opening, Heaven ſhall open as an eternal Manſion for you; Jeſus will open at this Day all his Store-houſes; the eternal Kingdom, the eternal Weight of Glory, and the Fulneſs of Joy that is in the Preſence of God, ſhall then open: All the unſeen things that are prepared for thoſe that love God, ſhall then open.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33599:60"/>(5.) At this Day the Righteouſneſs and Holineſs of God's Ways towards you will open before you, and you ſhall ſee a moſt clear and full Commentary on that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>All things ſhall work together for Good to them that love God,</hi> Rom. 8.28. All your Tears, Prayers, Sufferings, Patience, Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings out for God from firſt to laſt, ſhall at this Opening be found owned and crowned. Wherefore <hi>Comfort one another with theſe Words,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.18.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Errat.</hi> Page 52. Line 5, 6. read <hi>but they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33599:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
